<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly letter sent too the fayethfull in London, Newcastell, Barwyke, and to all other within the realme off Englande, that loue the co[m]minge of oure Lorde Iesus by Ihon Knox</title>
            <title>Admonition or warning that the faithful Christians in London, Newcastel Barwycke and others, may avoide Gods vengeaunce</title>
            <author>Knox, John, ca. 1514-1572.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1554</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15059.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843823</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843823</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8582</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8582)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 254:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly letter sent too the fayethfull in London, Newcastell, Barwyke, and to all other within the realme off Englande, that loue the co[m]minge of oure Lorde Iesus by Ihon Knox</title>
                  <title>Admonition or warning that the faithful Christians in London, Newcastel Barwycke and others, may avoide Gods vengeaunce</title>
                  <author>Knox, John, ca. 1514-1572.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28]; xviij, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By J. Lambrecht? for H. Singleton] before the Castel of s. Aungel, at the signe of sainct Peter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted in Rome [i.e. Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the moneth of Iuly, in the yeare of our Lord. 1554.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed at Wesel by J. Lambrecht? (STC).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁴; A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>"A confession [and] declaratio[n] of praiers added thervnto" has separate dated title page and register.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Also published the same year as: An admonition or warning that the faithful Christians in London, Newcastel Barwycke and others, may avoide Gods vengeaunce.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 15073 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mass --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:1"/>
                  <p>¶A godly let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſent too the fayethfull in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don / Newcaſtell / Barwyke / and to all other within the realme off Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande / that loue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge of oure LORDE Ieſus by Ihon Knox.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Math. 10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
☞He that continueth vnto the ende / ſhall be ſaued.</q>
                  <p>¶Imprinted in Rome, before the Caſtel of ſ. Aungel / at the ſigne of ſainct Peter. In the moneth of Iuly / in the yeare of our Lord. 1554. (?)</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Ihon Knox To the faythfull in Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtell / Barwyke / &amp; to all others / with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Realme of Englande / that le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uith the comming of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus / Wiſſheth continuance in godlines too the ende With a declaration of prayer / annexeth to the ſame.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the fearth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full threathninges of God / pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oficed againſt Realmes / <note place="margin">Leuit. xx Matth. x.</note> and na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions / to whom the light of Gods worde hath ben offered / and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptiouſly by them refuſed / as my hart vnfaynedly / morneth for your preſent eſtate / dearly beloued in our ſauiour Iheſus Chriſt / ſo doth the hole powers / of body &amp; ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le / trymble and ſhake / for the plagues that are to come. But that Gods trew worde hath ben offered to the realme of England can none de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye / except ſuche as by the dyuel holden in bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage (God iuſtly ſo puniſhing their proud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obediens) hath neither eyes to ſe / <note place="margin">Timo. ij.</note> nor vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to dycerne good from bad / nor darkenes from light. Againſt whome no otherwiſe will I contend at this preſent / then dyd the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete
<pb facs="tcp:8582:3"/>
Ieremie / againſt the ſtyffe necked &amp; ſtub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>borne people of Iuda / ſayinge:<note place="margin">Ierem. xxiii</note> 
                     <hi>The wrath off the Lord ſhall not be turned awaye, till he haue fulfilled the thoughtes of his hart.</hi> And thus leaue I them (as of whoſe repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there is ſmall hope) to the handes of hym that ſhall not forget their horrible blaſphemis ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in diſpitte of Chriſtes truthe / and of hys trew miniſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> And with you that vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly morneth for the greate ſhipwrake of goddes trew relygion / purpoſe I to communicat ſuche counſailer / and admonicious / now by my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge / as ſometymes it pleaſed God / I dyd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime in your cares. The ende of whiche my admonicion is / that euin as that you purpoſe / and entend to auoid Gods vengeaunce / bothe in this lyfe / and in the lyfe to come / that ſo ye auoid and flee (aſwell in body as in ſprete) al fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip / and ſocietye with Idolaters in their Idolatrye. You ſhrynke (I know) euin at the fyrſt. But yf an orator / had the matter in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge / he wolde proue it honeſte / profytable / ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye / and neceſſary to be done / and in euery one poynte were ſtore ynough / for a longe oration. But as I neuer labored to perſwade any man in matters of religion (God I take to record in my conſcience) except by the very ſimplicitie &amp; plaine infallable truthe of Gods worde. No more mynde I in this behaulfe. But this I af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrme / that to fle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> idolatrye / is ſo profytable and ſo neceſſary to a Chriſtian / that onles he ſo do / all worldly profyth turneth to his perpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall diſprofeit / and condemnacion. Profijt aperteyning / either to the bodyes / or to the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:8582:3"/>
/ of our ſelues / and our poſteritie / corporall commodities conſiſteth in ſuch thinges as man chiefly couetith for the body / as ryches / eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion / longe lyfe / health and quietnes in earth. The only comfort and ioye of the ſoule is God by his worde expelling ingoraunce / ſynne / and death / and in the place of thoſe / planting trew knowledge of hym ſelfe / and with theſame iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and lyfe / by Chriſt his ſonne. Yf any off theſe forſaide moue vs / then of neceſſitie it is / that we auoyde Idolatry / for playne it is / that the ſoule hath neither lyfe nor comfort / but by God alone / with whome Idolatours / <note place="margin">1. Cor. vl.</note> hath no other participacion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen hath the deuils / and albeit that abhominable Idolatours / for a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ryſiphe yet approcheth the houre / when Gods vengeaunce ſhall ſtryke / not onely their ſoules / but euin their vile carcaſies / ſhalbe pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gued / as God before hath threatned.<note place="margin">Leui. xxv</note> Their cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhalbe burned / their la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſhalbe layd waſt / their enemies ſhall dwell in their ſtronge hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / their wyues and doughters ſhalbe defyted their chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall fall in the edge of the ſwerd / mercy ſhall they fynde none / becauſe they haue refuſed the God of all mercye / when louingly and longe he called vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / you wolde know the tyme / and what certitude I haue here off. To God wil I appoint no tyme / but that theſe and mo plagues / ſhall fall vpon England (and that ere it he long) I am ſo ſure / as that I am that my God lyueth. This my affirmacion / ſhall diſpleaſe many / and ſhall content few / God knowith the ſecretes of all hartes / kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that alſo / it diſpleaſeth myſelfe / and yet
<pb facs="tcp:8582:4"/>
lyke as before I haue ben compelled to ſpeake in your preſens (&amp; in preſens of others) ſuche thinges / as were not pleaſable to the eares of men / wherof (alas) a great part this daye are come to paſſe / ſo I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled now to wryte with the teares of my eyes / I know to your diſpleaſur. But deare brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / be ſubiect vnto God / and geue place vnto his wrath / that ye may eſcape his euerlaſtinge vengeaunce. My penne I truſt / ſhall now be no more veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / then my tounge hath bene after then ones / not onely before you / but alſo before the chief of the Realme. What was ſayd in Newcaſtel &amp; Barwyke before the ſweat. I truſt yet ſom in thoſe places beareth in mynde / What vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the daye of all Sainctes / <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtel wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es.</note> the yeare that the duke of Somerſet was laſt apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. What before hym / that then was duke of Northum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berland / in the towne of Newcaſtell / &amp; other places moo: What before the kynges maieſtye at Wynſore / Hamptoncourt / and Weſtmyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter / &amp; fynally what was ſpoken in London / in moo places then one / when fyers of ioye &amp; ryotous bankettinge were made at the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamacion of Mary your quene. Yf men will not ſpeake / the ſtones and tymber of thoſe places / ſhal crye in fyer / and beare record that the truthe was ſpoken / and ſhal abſolue me / in that behalfe in the daye of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Suſpect not brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that I delyte in your calamities / or in the plagues that ſhal fal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that vnthankefull nation. No / God I take to recorde / that my hart mourneth within me / and that I am crucyet for remembraunce of
<pb facs="tcp:8582:4"/>
youre troubles / but if that I ſhoulde ceaſſe / then dyd I agaynſte my conſcience / as alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte my knowledge / <note place="margin">Eze. xxxiij</note> and ſo ſhoulde be gyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the bloud of thoſe that peryſhed for lack of admonicions / and yet ſhal the plague not a moment the longer be delayed / for the Lorde hath apoynted the daye of hys vengeaunce / before the whiche he ſendeth trompettes and meſſingers / that hys electe / watchynge with prayers / and ſobrietie / maye be hys mercye eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the vengeaunce that ſhal come. But now you wolde knowe the groundes of my certitude / God graundt that hearinge them / you maye vnderſtande / and ſtedfaſtlye beleue the ſame. My aſſurances are / not the maruai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les of Marlynge / neither yet the darke ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of prophaine Prophetes / but the playne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> truthe of Gods holy worde. The immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> iuſtice of the euerliuing God. And the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denary <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> courſe of hys plagues from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning are my aſſuraunces &amp; groundes. Gods worde threatneth diſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the inobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.<note place="margin">Deu. xxvii Ierem v. Amos. iij.</note> Hys immutable iuſtice muſte require the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame. The ordenarye puniſhmentes and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues ſheweth examples / What menne then hauynge vnderſtandynge / can ceaſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye?</p>
                  <p>The worde of God playnely ſpeaketh / <note place="margin">Deut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9.</note> that yf a man ſhal heare the curſes of Gods law / and yet in his hart ſhal promys to hym ſelfe / felicitie and good lucke / thinckinge / he ſhall haue peace / albeit he walcke after the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions of hys owne wil and hart. To ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:8582:5"/>
a man the Lord will not be mercifull / but hys wrath ſhalbe kyndled againſt him / and he ſhal deſtroye hys name fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the heauen / how the Lord threathneth plagues after plague / and euer the laſt to be the fyrſt / whill fynally / he will conſume realmes / and nations / if they re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent not / reade the .26. Chapter off <hi>Leuiticus</hi> / which chapter / oft I haue willed you to marke / as yet I do vnfainedly / anh thinke not / it apre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth to the Iewes only / <hi>No brethern.</hi> The Prophetes are the interparatours of the law / and they make the plagues off God commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all offendore / the punyſhment euer beginning at the houſhold of God.<note place="margin">
                        <p>The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the late duke off Northu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / at the hour of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath / aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynſte hys owne con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience in hope off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yfe.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Eſai. xiij.xv.xviij.cvij.xix. Ieremi. l lj. Ezech. xxv xxvi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>7.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </note> And here I muſt tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a poinct off that deuilliſhe confeſſion made (a late) by that miſerable man / whoſe name for ſorow I can not recyte. This argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he vſeth to proue the doctrine of late yeres done / taught amongeſt you / to be wicked / Trobles and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues (ſayth he) hath folowed the ſame / not only here in England / but alſo in Germany / as he willeth you to marke. This fragill / and vaine argument at this tyme / no otherwyſe will I labor / to confute / then by plaine ſcriptures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring / that plagues apertayneth to all inobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient / beginninge firſte / where Gods mercies hath bene offered / and obſtinatly refuſed / &amp; that may aunſwere the blynde rage of ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces.</p>
                  <p>The Prophetes <hi>Eſai, Ieremi, Ezechieli,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had proclaymed plagues to fall vppon the people off Iſrael / and vpon the houſe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>da / prophecyeth particularlye againſte certeyn nations and cyties / not onely adiace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in circute about Ieruſalem / but alſo againſte ſuche / as
<pb facs="tcp:8582:5"/>
were far diſtant / as againſt <hi>Moah, Ammon, Paleſtina, Aegipt, Tirus, Damaſcus, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilone.</hi> And in concluſion generall propheſies / are ſpoken againſt all inobedient / and ſynfull natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / as in the .24. chapter off <hi>Eſaye</hi> plainly apeareth / <note place="margin">Ierem. xxv</note> as alſo the Lord commaunding Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye / to geue the cuppe off hys wrath / to al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions / one after another / who ſholde drinke off the ſame / although they refuſed it of his hand / That is albeit / they wolde not beleue the voyce off the prophet / yet ſholde they not eſcape.<note place="margin">Ierem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> The plagues that he ſpake. <hi>For euery nation lyke vnto this</hi> / ſhal I puniſſhe ſaith the Lord of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes / with theſame agreeth <hi>Amos ſaing:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos. ix.</note> 
                     <hi>The eyes of the Lord are vpon euery ſinfull na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to roote it out of the earthe.</hi> Theſe and many mo places euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly proueth that plagues ſpoke in the law of God / apertaineth to euery rebellions people / be they Iew / or be they Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile / Chriſtians intytel / or Turkes in profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / And the grounde off the Prophetes / was the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame / <note place="margin">The iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of God</note> whiche before I haue reherſed for my aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuraunces / that Englande ſhall be plagued / which is Godes immutable and inuiolable iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtice / whiche can not ſpare in one Realme and nation / thoſe offences that moſte ſeuerally he hath puniſſhed in another / for ſo were he in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall and made differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / as touching executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off his iuſt iudgementes / betwixte parſon and parſon / whiche is moſt contrarious to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie off his iuſtice / for thus he ſpeaketh by <hi>Ieremy</hi> his prophete: <hi>Behold,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ierem. xxv</note> 
                     <hi>I haue bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne</hi> to puniſſhe in the houſe where my name is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called / and <hi>ſhall I ſpare the reſt,</hi> as the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:8582:6"/>
wolde ſaye / howe can my iuſtice permit thoſe crymes vnpuniſhed in proude contemptnors / that neither regardeth me / nor yet my lawe / ſeing I haue not ſpared my own people / that externally beareth ſome reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to my name.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Englande ſynfull.</note>That God hath puniſhed other realmes &amp; nations / men of ſmal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding / wil eaſly confes. But whether that lyke crymes hathe ben / and yet are committed within the realme of Englande / as were before the laſte plagues of God among thoſe nations / that is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred / in this caſe can nothing better inſtruct vs then Gods plaine woorde / rebuking the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / whiche raigned in thoſe dayes / And omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all ſuch as propheſied before / it ſhal ſuffice for this tyme / to reherſe ſome places of Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye. The tyme of whoſe prophecie wel conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered / ſhal make the matter more ſenſible. He beginneth in the .13. yeare of the raigne of king <hi>Ioſias</hi> and contine with tyll after the deſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieruſalem / whiche came in the .11. yeare of <hi>Zedechias</hi> / Longe preached this godly man to wite .39. yeares and ſixe monethes / before the vttermoſt of the plagues apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded this ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born nation and that he did with much troble and iniurie ſuſteined / as in his propheſyes / is to be ſene. Be all lykelyhold then / there were ſome Cob Carles / that were not pleaſed with the proffit / neither yet with hys preachinges. And yet plaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t is / that no Kyng ſo truly tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto God with all hys hart / with all hys ſoule / and with all hys ſtrength / accordinge to all the law of Moyſes / as did Ioſias / &amp; yet as ſayd is. The prophet of God was trobled / not
<pb facs="tcp:8582:6"/>
by no ſmal number / for I fynd hym complain / vniuerſally &amp; generally vpon the peoples ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie / for thus iudgeth he Gods ſpeakinge. My people haue committed dubble iniquitie.<note place="margin">Ierem. ij.</note> They haue forſaken me / the fountaine of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning water / and haue digged to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtornes / that can holde no water. Why wilt thou iuſtefye thyſelfe? Vnder thy wynges is founde the bloud of the ſoules of the poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentes / whome thou founde not in corners / and yet thou ſayeſt / I am innocent.<note place="margin">Ierem. iij.</note> Thou haſt gotten a whores forehead / thou canſt not think ſhame / my people is foliſh / they know me not / <note place="margin">Ierem. iiij. Ierem i.ix.</note> they are folyſh chyldren / and haue no wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wiſe they are to committe miſchiefe / but to do good they are all together ignorant. Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may beware of his neyghbor / and no man aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly maye truſte in hys brother / for euery man is beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eatfull / they haue practeſed their tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to lyes / and guyle. They haue lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my law (ſayth the Lord) and haue folowed the wicked imaginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of their owne hartes / they haue folowed after Baalam / whome their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers taught them.<note place="margin">The offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>da before the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie.</note> Of this and of many moo places lyke apeareth the generall offences / off that people to haue ben defectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God / ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloud / Iuſtifiyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes / &amp; defence of their iniquitie / while yet they abeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded in reaf / murder / oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / lyes / crafte / pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe / deceat / &amp; manifeſt idolatrye / folowing the trade of their fathers / who vnder <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ammo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> / of whom the one in the beginning / tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther all his lyfe mantaineth Idolatrie / had ben the ringleders of all abhominacion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8582:7"/>The prophetes off God wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering at ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt iniquitie iudged that ſuche ingnorauncy and inobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was only amonges the raſcals ſorte off men / and therfore he ſayth:<note place="margin">Ierem. v.</note> Theſe be but poore ones / they are foliſſhe / they knowe not the waye of the Lord / nor the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t off their God / I will goo to the nobils and I will talke with them / for they know the waye off theyr Lord / and the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of their God. But what findeth he amonges them / he decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red in theſe wordes,<note place="margin">Ierem. v.</note> 
                     <hi>They haue all broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yocke,</hi> they haue heaped ſynne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne / and one miſſchefe vpon another / fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leaſt vnto the moſte / all are bent vpon auaryce / and gape for lucre / from the prieſt to the prophet / euery man dealth deceatfully.<note place="margin">Ierem. vi.</note> Beholde / theyr eares be incircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed / they can not aduert / The word of God is a rebuke vnto them / they delite not in it. They haue committed abhominable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchiefe / What this abhomination was / God ſheweth to Ezechiel / <note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>k viii.</note> all had forſaken God in their hartes / in ſo muche that a great number openly / had turned their backes vnto God / and made ſacrifice to the ſunne / euery man in hys owne ſecret cloſet. Yea / wemen mourned for that they were not permitted to commit open abhomination / is it not to be wondered that al eſtates were ſo corrupte vnder ſo godly a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.<note place="margin">Ierem. v.</note> But our prophet Ieremie proceadith in his complainte / ſayinges / they can not repent / nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet thinke ſhame. They haue denied the Lord / and ſayd it is not he / we ſhall neither ſe ſweard nor hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. You heare the obediens that the prophet founde amonges the princes off
<pb facs="tcp:8582:7"/>
Iuda / and yet I ſaye / it is not to be wondered that the vineyarde / which was ſo well mannu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red / brought forth no better grapes.<note place="margin">Herken England.</note> They had a kyng moſt godly mynded / they had prophetes (for Ieremy was not alone) moſt faithful and ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. They were admoniſſhed by diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues / and alwaies the prophetes called for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce / and yet folowed nothing / but open conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt off God / and of hys meſſingers.<note place="margin">Oſel. vl.</note> Their repentaunce were lyke the mornyng dewe / it remayned not / although they cold ſaye in their mouthe / the Lord lyueth / yet were their othes nothinge but lyes.<note place="margin">Ierem. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Fynde me one man / that doth equitie &amp; iuſtice &amp;c. to hym will I be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull ſayth the Lord. Here was narow and ſharpe inquiſition amonges ſo great a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude be lyke / there hath not bene very manye / when he that knoweth the ſecrete thoughtes ſearcheth ſo dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. But before we proceade further in this matter / it ſhall be profytable / to ſe how theſe procedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges doth agree with our eſtate and tyme.<note place="margin">Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixte England and Iuda before the diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Kyng <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixte.</note> And firſte that we had not Gods woorde offered vnto vs / will none (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte arrant papiſt) alledge. We had a kynge off ſo godly diſpoſition towardes vertew / and chiefly towardes Gods truthe / that none fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynninge paſſed hym / and to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge / none of hys yeare did euer matche hym in that behalfe / iff he might haue bene lorde of hys owne will. In this meane tyme / if ſynnes dyd abound / let euery man accuſe hys owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience for here I am not mynded to ſpecefie all that I knowe / neither yet is it neceſſarye / ſeynge ſome crymes were ſo manifeſte and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8582:8"/>
heighnous that the earthe colde not hydde the innocent bloud / nor yet could the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhame / behold the craft / the deceat / the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens and wronge / that openly was wroughte. And in the meane ceaſon / the hande off God was buſye ouer vs / &amp; his trew meſſingers is kept not ſylence. You know that the realme off Englande was viſited with ſtraunge plagues and whether that it was euer propheſied / that the worſe plagues were to folow / I appeale to the teſtemony of your own conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / but what enſewed here vpon? Alas I am aſhamed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſe it / vniuerſal contempt of all godly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions / hatered of thoſe that rebuked their vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces: Autoreſing of ſuche / as colde inuente moſt vylanye agaynſte the preachers of God.<note place="margin">Witnes certeyne ballates.</note> In this matter I maye be admitted for a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t witnes / for I hard and ſaw / I vnderſtood and knew / with the ſorow of my hart / the manifeſt contempt and the crafty deuices of the deuil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe moſt godly and learned preachers, that this laſte Lent / Anno. 1553. were apoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to preache before the Kynges maieſtie / as alſo againſt all others / whoſe tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges were not tempered by the holy water of the courte too ſpeake it plainlye / who flatteringe agaynſte their owne conſcience / coulde not ſaye / all was well / and nothinge neded reformacion.</p>
                  <p>What reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and audience was geuen vnto preachers / this laſte Lent / by ſuch as then were in autoritie / their owne countinaunces declared aſſuredly / euen ſuche as was geuen to <hi>Ieremye</hi> / they hated ſuche / as rebuked their vyce / and ſtubbernlye they ſayde: We
<pb facs="tcp:8582:8"/>
wil not amende / and yet howe boldely theyr ſynnes were rebuked / ſuche as were preſente / can witnes with me / almoſte there was none / who dyd not propheſye and plainly ſpake the plagues that are begonne / and aſſuredly ſhall ende. Mayſter Grindall plainlye ſpake the death of the Kynges maieſtie / <note place="margin">Mayſter Grindal.</note> complayninge vppon hys houſholde ſeruauntes / who / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feared to raile agaynſte the woorde off God / and agaynſte the trewe preachers of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>That godly and feruent man mayſter Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer / playnlye ſpake the deſolacion off thys common wealthe.<note place="margin">Mayſter Leuer. Mayſter Bradford</note> And mayſter Bradforde (whome God for Chriſtes hys ſonne ſacke comforte to the ende) ſpared not the proudeſt of them / but boldely declared / that Goddes vengeaunce ſhortlye ſhoulde ſtrycke / thoſe that then were in auctoritie / becauſe they lothed &amp; abhorred the trew worde of the euerlaſtinge God / &amp; willed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take example by a noble man / who became ſo colde in hearing Gods worde / that the year before his death / he wold not diſeaſe hym ſelf to heare a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / God pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſſhed hym (ſayde that godly preacher) and ſhall he ſpare you that be dubble more wicked? No / ye ſhal ſaye / will ye / or will ye not / ye ſhal drinke of the cup of the Lordes wrathe / <hi>Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium domini, Iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mayſter Haddon.</note> The iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Lord / the iudgement of the Lorde / cryed he with a lamentable voyce / and weaping tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Maſter Haddon / moſt lernedly opened the cauſes of the byepaſſed plagues / and aſſured them / that the worſe was after to come / If re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce
<pb facs="tcp:8582:9"/>
ſhortly were not founde. Muche more I harde of theſe foure / and of others / which now I maye not rehearce / &amp; that (which is to be noted) after that the hole counſail had ſayd they wolde heare no mo of their ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / they were vndiſcrete felowes / yea / &amp; pratynge knaues / but I will not ſpeake all / for yf God contynew me in this troble. I purpoſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a dyſſhe / forſuche as then ledde the ryng / yea / who but they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but nowe they haue bene at the ſkoole of <hi>Placebo</hi> / and ther they haue lerned amongſt ladyes to daunſe as the deuill lyſt to pype. Agaynſt thoſe / whom God hath ſtryken / ſeing now reſteth to them no place of repentaunce / nothing mynd I to ſpeake. But ſuch as lyue to this dai / wold be admoniſſhed that he that hath puniſhed the one / wil not ſpare the reſt <hi>But to our matter.</hi> This preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents I iudge ſufficient to proue this oure age to haue bene / &amp; yet to remayne lyke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked (if it be not worſe) with the tyme of Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye. Now let vs ſearche what folowed in Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>da? Miſchefe vpon miſchefe / notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge the continuall and long cryeng of the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / whil fynally God in his anger toke away good king Ioſias / <note place="margin">liij. Regum xxllj.</note> becauſe he was determened to deſtroye Iuda / as before he had deſtroyed Iſrael. After the death of this godly Kynge / great was the troble / diuers &amp; ſondry were the alteracions in that comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth. Three kynges taken pryſoners / one after other in ſhort ſpace / what other were the miſeries of that ſtubbern nation. <hi>O God, for thy greate mercies ſake,</hi> let neuer thy ſmal and troubled
<pb facs="tcp:8582:9"/>
flocke / within the realme of Englande / learn in experiens. But in all thoſe trobles / no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce appeared / as by the prophet ye may learne / for thus he crieth:<note place="margin">Ierem. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Eſai. 1.</note> Thou haſte ſtryken them o Lorde / but they haue not mourned / thou haſt deſtroyed them / but they haue not receaued diſcipline.<note place="margin">Ieremi. xij.</note> They haue hardened their faces harder then ſtones / they will not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert: The hole la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is waſted / but no man wil wyn / <note place="margin">Ierem. xiij.</note> ponder &amp; conſider / the cauſe. This people will not heare my worde / They walke in the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked inuention of their owne hartes: They go after other goddes to worſhip and ſerue them and of the prophetes naturall frendes of the men of Anathotes / ſome plainly ſaid. Speake no more to vs in the name of the Lorde / leaſte thou dye in our handes / belyke theſe men had ſmal fantaſye to Gods prophet. But yet ſhall a ſermon (and that whiche enſewid the ſame) made in the beginning of the raigne of <hi>Iehoia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kim</hi> / ſonne to <hi>Ioſias</hi> / make euident / and better knowne / how muche the people were bent to Idolatrye / and to heare falſe prophetes / after the death of their good kyng. The prophet is commaunded by God to ſtande in the court or entres of the Lordes houſe / and to ſpeake to all cities of Iuda / that then came to worſhippe / in the houſe of the Lorde / and is commaunded to kepe no worde backe / yf peraduenture (ſayeth the Lorde) they will herken and tourne euery man from his wicked waye. The tenor of hys ſermon / is this / <hi>Thus fayth the Lorde:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iere. xxvi.</note> yf ye wil not obey me to walke in my lawes / which I haue geuen you / and to heare the wordes of
<pb facs="tcp:8582:10"/>
my ſeruauntes the prophetes whome I ſente vnto you / ryſing vp betymes and ſtyl ſending / yf ye wil not heare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I ſayde) then wil I do to this houſe / as I dyd vnto Silo / &amp; will make this citie / to be abhorred of al the people in the earth. Heare not the wordes of the prophetes / that ſaid vnto you / you ſhal not ſerue the king of Babylon / <note place="margin">Iere. 27.</note> I haue not ſent them (ſayeth the Lorde) howbeit / they are bold to propheſye lyes in my name / yf you geue eare vnto them / both you and your falſe prophetes ſhal periſh:<note place="margin">Denie vvil I nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. But the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e vvas done in Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande.</note> Here is firſt to be noted / that the people was alredy entered in to iniquitie / and eſpecially ſtraighte after the death of their king / into Idolatry / fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the Lorde by his prophet labored to call them backe / threatning vnto them deſolation / yf they procede to rebel.<note place="margin">Suche falſe prophetes at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente are muche eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande.</note> Secondarely / it is to be obſerued / that amongeſt them were falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes / not that they were ſo knowen / &amp; holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the people / no / they were holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and eſtemed for ſo they boaſted them ſelfes to be. The trew churche of God that colde not erre / for howe ſhould the law periſh from the mouthe of the preaſts.<note place="margin">Ierem. 18</note> Theſe falſe prophetes were mayntay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of Idolatrie / and yet boldelye promiſed to the people proſperitie and good lucke. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the people were ſo abuſed and blinded / that the wordes of Ieremye / dyd rather harde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their hartes / then prouoke any to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taunce / as the conſequentes declared / for his ſermon ended / the prieſtes / prophetes / and the hole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple apprehended Ieremye / and with one voyce cryed / he is worthye of the death. Greate was
<pb facs="tcp:8582:10"/>
the vprore agaynſt the poore prophet / <note place="margin">Ierem. 26</note> in which appearinglye / he coulde not haue eſcaped the death. Yf the princes of Iuda / had not haſtelye comme from the kynges houſe / in to the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple / and had taken vppon them / the hearinge of the cauſe / in which after much debate (while ſome defendid and ſome accuſed the prophet moſt ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hemently) the text ſayth / that the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of <hi>Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kan</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Saphan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the true pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers are caſte into priſon, &amp; no cauſe kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vven vvhi.</note> was with Ieremye / that he ſhould not be geuen into the handes off the people / to be kylled. Hereof you may eaſlye conſider (beloued brethren) what were the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of that wicked generacion immediatly / after the death of their good kynge / and howe they were encoraged to Idolatrye by falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes / but in all this tyme / the prophete cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not moſt faythfully / to execute his office / for albeit after this he mighte not enter in the temple (for he was forbidden to preache)<note place="margin">Ier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 36.</note> yet at Gods commaundement / he writinge hys ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons / and cauſing them to be openly redde in the temple (alas I feare we lacke Baruck) and after they come to the eares of the counſail / &amp; laſte to the kynge. And albeit in diſpyte they were ones brent / Yet is Ieremy commaunded to writte agayn / and boldely to ſay: <hi>Iehoiakim ſhall haue no ſede, that euer ſhall ſit vppon the ſeate of Dauid.</hi> Their carion ſhalbe caſten to the heate of the daye / and to the fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt in the night / and I ſhal viſet ſayeth the Lord the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of hym / of his ſede and of hys ſeruaſites / and I ſhal bring vpon them / vpon the dwellers in Ieruſalem and vpon all Iuda / all the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that I haue ſpoken agaynſt them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8582:11"/>Albeit / when theſe wordes were ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and written / ſo they were contempned / that they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt crye / <hi>Let the counſaill of the holy one of Iſraell come,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iere. xviij.</note> 
                     <hi>we will folow the deuiſes of our owne hartes</hi> / yet no worde of his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges were ſpoken in vayne / for after many plagues ſuſteyned by the miſſchefes father / the wicked and myſerable ſonne in the thyrde moneth of his raigne was led pryſoner to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.<note place="margin">iiij. Regum xxiiij.</note> But now when the tyme of their deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation approcheth / <note place="margin">There are to many off ſuche prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, novv in Englande.</note> God ſtyred aboue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche a kyng / ſuche prophetes and prieſtes / as their owne hartes wiſhed / euen ſuche as ſhoulde without repugnaunce / leade them to their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met agayne / that they who neuer delyted in the truthe / might fyll their bellyes with horryble lyes.<note place="margin">Ieremie. xxx viii.</note> 
                     <hi>Zedechias</hi> was kyng / and ſuche as longe had reſiſted poore <hi>Ieremye</hi> / had now gotten in their hande / the fearfull whippe of correction <hi>Paschar</hi> / and hys companyons ledde the kynge as they lyft / vn goith Topeth (a place of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie) the hill Aulters ſmoketh with incenſe:<note place="margin">Aduertie Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s dyd Iuda.</note> Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l and hys bellye G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ddes / before the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of God / was poured vpon them / &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them whome they deceauid / gettet the day thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> longe loked for. Inconcluſion / ſo horrible were the abhominations that newly were erected / <note place="margin">As Pas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> ruled the Kyng than at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur, ſo doth the B. of Vvinche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter rule the quene novv, and doth vvhat him luſteth in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. O vvicced<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Iere. xi.</note> that the Lord cryeth to hys ſore trobled flocke / what hath my welbeloued too do in my houſe (meaning in the temple of Ieruſalem) ſeynge the multitude committeth ſuch abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / they haue prouoked me to anger / burninge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe vnto Baäl.</p>
                  <p>Whiche great abhominations / when God
<pb facs="tcp:8582:11"/>
had ſhewin / not onlye to Ieremie / who then was in Ieruſalem / but alſo to <hi>Ezechiel</hi> being priſoner in Babylon. Their bodies being ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated / in prophecie they did bothe agre / that hole Iſrael &amp; Iuda ſhould be deſtroied. Thus writeth <hi>Ezechiel</hi> / Ah / vpon all the abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the houſe of Iſrael / they ſhal fal by the ſwearde / by peſtilence and hunger / he that is far of ſhall dye of the plagues / he that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye / ſhal fal by the ſwearde / he that is lefte / and is beſeaged / ſhal dye by hunger / and I ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plet my wrath vpon them. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſayth: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold / I wil geue this citie in the handes of the Caldees / in the hande of Nabuchod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſer / kyng of Babylon / who ſhal take it.<note place="margin">Ieremie xxxij.</note> The Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees verely ſhal entre in to it / &amp; they ſhal burn i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with fyre / &amp; the houſes in which they burnt incenſe to Baal. &amp;c. The chyldren of Iſraell &amp; the chyldren of Iuda had done nothinge frome their youth / but wickednes &amp; that before my eyes to prouoke me to anger / They haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto me their backes / and not their faces: They / their kynges / their princes / <note place="margin">All the gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies off the papiſtes are very donge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion before God.</note> their prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / their prieſtes / hole Iuda and all the citie of Ieruſalem / they wolde not heare / and be refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med. They haue ſet vp their do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge (ſo tearmeth he their Idols) in the place that is conſecrate to my name. And where the kyng of Babylon was lyeng about the citie / he ſayth to the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyngers of <hi>Zedechias</hi> (who were ſente to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of the prophete / what ſhould become of the citie).<note place="margin">Ierem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e. xxxvij.</note> 
                     <hi>The Caldees ſhall take this citie and ſhall burne it with fyre:</hi> Yea / if you had kylled al the hoſte of the Caldees that beſageth
<pb facs="tcp:8582:12"/>
you / <note place="margin">Vvho vvolde not haue called the prophet a traitour Iere. 38.</note> &amp; if they kylled / me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were left / euery man ſhould ryſe in hys tent / and ſhould burne this citie with fyre / he that abideth in this citie ſhal dye / either by ſweard / by hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger / or by peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / but he that ſhal go furthe to the Caldees / ſhal lyue / &amp; ſhal wynne hys ſoule for a praye / And to the kynge in ſecret aſkinge hys counſaile / he boldly ſayeth / yf ſodenly thou ſhalt go forth to the princes of the Babylonians. Thy ſoule ſhal lyue / and this citie ſhall not be brent with fyre / but and yf thou go not forthe to the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the Babylonians / this citie ſhalbe geuen ouer into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of the Caldees / who ſhal burne it with fyre / neither ſhalte thou eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape their handes. Thus did theſe two prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes (as alſo did others) before them plainlye ſpeake the deſolation of that place / for ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences / as before hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rehearſed. But how pleaſeth ſuch meſſaige the citie of Ieruſalem? the prieſtes / princes &amp; people of Iuda? &amp; what reward receaueth Ieremie for hys longe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle and painfull preachinge.<note place="margin">The cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes layd againſte Ieremy <hi>Iere, 9.23 Ezec. 20.</hi>
                     </note> Verely / euin ſuch as Paſhur &amp; his counſail iudgeth mete. <hi>He ſpake againſt the temple, he prophecied miſchief againſt the citie, he fainted the har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the ſouldiours, and of the people, but principally,<note place="margin">Such vve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>althe do the papiſtes promis the people for receauinge the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous maſſe, againe into Englande. Iere. 28.</note> he was vnfrendly to the faythe, that Paſſhur taught the people:</hi> To weke / the fayth of their forefathers / who alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled agaynſt God. And therefore he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a heretycke / accuſed of ſedicion / and dampned of treaſon. Playne preachinges were made agaynſte all that he had ſpoken / and ſuche felicitie was promiſed / that within
<pb facs="tcp:8582:12"/>
twoo yeares ſhoulde the yocke of Nabucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſor be broken from the neckes of all people and the veſſels of the lordes houſe (together with all pryſoners) ſhould be brought agayne to Ieruſalem.<note place="margin">Iere. 13. Habo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce cam before the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Iere. 38.</note> Now dyd this habound with wyne &amp; oyle / <hi>O pleaſing and bleſſed</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the people were ſuch prophetes / <hi>Ieremy had trobled them,</hi> and therefore he muſt dye. To pryſon ſhall he go / for the kyng can denye no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to his princes / of whome Paſhur apea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth / to haue ben chief chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celour / by whom was not only the kyng / but alſo the hole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude ſo blinded / that boldly they durſt crye: <hi>No miſchaunce ſhall come too vs, we ſhall neither ſe peſtilens nor hunger. The kynge of Babylon ſhall neuer come againſte thys lande.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iere. 27</note> In the middeſt of theſe ſtormy trob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / no other comfort had the prophet / then to complayn to hys God / at whoſe commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment he had ſpoken. And in this his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint he is ſo kyndled agaynſt their Idolatrie / and great vnthankefulnes that he crieth / as in a raige. <hi>O thou Lord of hoſtes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iere. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.</note> 
                     <hi>the tryar of the iuſt, thou that ſeith the reynes and the hart, Let me ſe thy vengeaunce taken vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for vnto the haue I referred my cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this prayer was moſt fearful to his enemyes / yf they had ſene the effiaccie therof ſo by the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame was the prophet aſſured / that Goddes wrath was kyndled againſt that ſinful natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; that it ſhoulde not turne backe / till he had performed the cogitations of his owne hart. <hi>I appeale to the conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> / of euery indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / in what one point differeth the regiment
<pb facs="tcp:8582:13"/>
manners / <note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; Iuda.</note> and eſtate of Englande this day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the aboue rehearſed eſtate off Iuda in thoſe dayes / except that they had a kynge / a man (as apeareth) of nature / more facied / nor cruell / who ſometymes was entreated in the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes fauour / and alſo requyred hym of counſail in ſome daungers.<note place="margin">The quene ſtubburne againſt the truthe of gods vvord and hateful to the prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers of the ſame.</note> And you haue a Quene / a woman of a ſtoute ſtomack / more ſtyffe in opy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion / then flexible too the truthe / who in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe maye abyde the preſens of Gods prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. In this one thing you diſagre in al other thinges ſo lyke as one nut is too another. <hi>Their kyng led by peſtilence prieſtes</hi> / who guides your quene / it is not vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Vnder ſuch came Idolatrie to the highte agayne. O wold to God / that the worſe were not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you / <hi>In Ieruſalem was Ieremie perſecuted</hi> / for ſpeakinge the truthe / &amp; for rebuking their Idolatrie. What pryſon within London / tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth not ſome trew prophet of God?<note place="margin">The Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous maſſe of late. firſt erected in the tovver of London.</note> for the ſame cauſes: <hi>And o thou doungeon off darkenes</hi> where that Idole of late dayes was fyrſt erected <hi>(thou Tower of London)</hi> in the doth moo Ieremies then one ſuffer iniurye &amp; trouble / <note place="margin">The B. of Canterb. D. Ridleye. M. Latimer Bradforde. Sandes. Becon. Veron. &amp;c. Preachers and priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the Tovver of London.</note> whome God ſhal comfort according to hys promyſe / and reward their perſecutors euen as they haue deſerued / and in that daye ſhalt thou trymble / and ſuche as ſhal purpoſe to defende the / ſhal periſhe with the / becauſe thou waſte fyrſt defyled with that moſt abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Idol.</p>
                  <p>Conſider (deare brethern) if all thinges / as appertayninge to iniquitie be a lyke betwixte Englande and Iuda / before the deſtruccion
<pb facs="tcp:8582:13"/>
therof / yea / Yf Englande be worſe then Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea was in thoſe dayes / ſeing God ſpared not them / ſhal we thinke that the Lordes venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce ſhal ſlepe / mans iniquitie beyng ſo rype? No deare brethren:<note place="margin">Iere. ix.</note> 
                     <hi>He that hath vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge muſte know the contrary, And he to whome the Lordes mouth hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> / muſt ſhew the cauſes / why the lande ſhalbe waſte.</p>
                  <p>It maye offende you / that I cal Englande worſe / then was vnthankeful Iudea / but yf good and euident reaſones aduiſed maye take place / then I feare not iudgement.<note place="margin">Wherein Iudea was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then England is now.</note> From Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem / many paſſed at admonition of the prophetes / leauing all that they had / rather then they wolde abyde the daunger of Gods plagues that were threatned. Goddes prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes hath cryed. but I heare not of many that prepareth to flye / God graunte they repent not. In Ieruſalem were princes / &amp; noble men who defended <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and alſo that dyd ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue hym / when wrongfully he was accuſed by the prieſtes. But howe many now of the nobilitie within Englande boldely ſpeaketh in in the defence of Gods meſſinger is eaſy too be tolde. Amongeſt them had Gods prophet ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty / to ſpeake in maintenaunce of his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. How ſuch as ſeketh a tryal of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine / hath bene and are entreated amongeſt you / it is hard of in ſtraunge countries. In Ieruſalem was Abdemelech / why when the prophet was caſt in pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as worthy of death) boldly paſt to the king / and defending the inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cency of the innocent / obtayneth hys liberty / but in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d I hear of none (God ſtur ſome)
<pb facs="tcp:8582:14"/>
that dare be ſo bolde / as to put their handes betwixt the Lyons / and their praye / the poore ſainctes of God / &amp; thoſe cruell murtherers. In Ieruſalem / Ieremy beyng dampned to pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / was fedde of the kynges charges / &amp; that when great hunger and ſcante of bread was in the hole citie: In London where all plenty haboundes / are Gods meſſingers permitted to hunger. Yea / (O horrable to be harde) and aunciente fathers / are ſo cruelly entreated / that lyke extremetye hath ſeldom bene vſed vpon theues and murtherers. In this behalf do I not blame you (beloued brethren) for I aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuredly know your hartes to mourn for the trobles of your brethren / and faythfull prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and that you ſeke all meanes poſſible / how they maye be comforted &amp; releaued / but theſe thinges to thende that you mayeſe / that more abhominacion / &amp; leſſe fear of God / more in iuſt dealing / and leſe ſhame more cruel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecucion againſt Gods meſſengers / and leſſe mercy and gentlenes / is now amongſt youre chief rulars within Englande / then in thoſe dayes was in Iudea / and yet did not Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſcape the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God.<note place="margin">Bevvare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling goſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, vvhich for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oure vvorld lij pelfe defile four ſelfes vvith all po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſhe abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacions.</note> Shall we then beleue that England maye auoide the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce that is threatned / <hi>No deare brethren, Yf Idolatrie continew</hi> / as it is begonne / no more can England eſcape Gods vengeaunce / then God hym ſelf may leaſe his iuſtice. And therfore (dearly beloued in our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt) Yf profit to your ſelfe or to your poſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie can moue you any thinge / then muſte ye avoide and fle Idolatrie. For if the Lordes
<pb facs="tcp:8582:14"/>
meſſengers / that ſhalbe ſente too execute hys wrath / fynde you amongſt fylthie Idolators / your bodies committing lyke abhomination with them. Ye haue no warrant that ye ſhall eſcape the plagues / prepared for the wicked. But rather it is to be feared that ye ſhall be plagued with them.<note place="margin">Iudi. 20</note> 
                     <hi>The hole trybe of Benia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>min,</hi> periſhed with the adulterers / &amp; yet were they not all adulterers in faict.<note place="margin">1. Reg 15</note> Hole Amalek was commaunded to be deſtroyed / &amp; yet was not one of thoſe lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that trobled the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites / in their paſſage from Egipte. Pharao was not drouned alone (as in another letter / I haue more plainly writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) neither yet fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Ionathas mercy / as touchinge lyfe corporal / in the daye when Gods vengeaunce puniſhed Saule the repobater / and why? the Apoſtle aunſwereth:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Becauſe men knowing the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God,</hi> (ſayeth he) and doing the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary are worthy of death / not only thoſe that doth wickedly / but alſo ſuche as conſenteth to the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame.<note place="margin">Who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth.</note> And no man can be excuſed / but that he conſentes / who dayly frequenting in the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panye of wicked men / geuinge neither ſigne in woordes nor in dede / that iniquitie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth hym. And therefore yet I ſaye / yf profyt may moue vs. &amp;c. moſt profytable ſhall it be euen for the body in this preſent lyfe too auoide Idolatrye / for ſo doinge / As we ſhal eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the plagues / whiche the vngodlye ſhall ſuffer / ſo is God by hys promis obliſhed vnto vs to be our father / our portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / <note place="margin">Eſai. 49. Zacha. 2.</note> our i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>heritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce &amp; defence / he promiſeth (&amp; wil not diſceaue)
<pb facs="tcp:8582:15"/>
to cary vs vppon hys owne wynges from all daunger.<note place="margin">Pſal. lij. Pſalm. c.xlvi. Pſalm. c.xl.</note> To plant vs &amp; our poſteritie in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting memorial. To feade vs in the tyme off hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger / and fynally to fight for vs / and to ſaue vs from all miſeries and miſchaunces, <hi>But now to the ſubſequent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As it is moſt profytable for body and ſoule to auoyde Idolatry / ſo is it ſo neceſſary / that onles we ſo do / we refuſe to be in leage with God.<note place="margin">What we doo when we ioyn our ſelfs with idolaters <hi>Exo. xx.</hi>
                     </note> We declare ourſelf to haue no faythe / &amp; we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enye to be Gods witnes / and ſo muſte he of this iuſtice expreſſed in his worde denye vs to apertaine to hym or to hys kyngdom. And then (alas) what reſtith for vs / but perpetuall death ordeined for thoſe that wil not continew in leage with God. The leage betwene God &amp; vs conteyneth theſe conditions / that God ſhall be our God / and we ſhal be his people / he ſhal communicat with vs / of his graces &amp; goodnes we ſhal ſerue hym in bodye &amp; ſoule / he ſhall be our ſauegarde from death and damnacion / we ſhal ſticke too hym / and fle from all ſtraunge Goddes. This is the leage in making whereof we ſwear ſolempnedly / neuer to haue felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with any religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / except with that which God hath auctoriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d by hys manifeſt worde. Yf by Gods ſcriptures theſe preſydents be ſo playne / that reaſonably no man can de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye any point therof. Then haue I good hope that ye wil admitte it to be neceſſarie / that you auoide Idolatry / yf the leage betwene God and you ſhalbe kept ſure. And fyrſt it is to be obſerued / that Goddes iuſtice / beyng infinite in matters of religion / requireth lyke obediens of al thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:8582:15"/>
that be within hys leage at all tymes / that he requireth of any one nation / or particular ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any one age / for al that byde with i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his leage / <note place="margin">Deu. 29.</note> are one body (as Moyſes doth witnes) recomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting men / wemen / chyldren / ſeruauntes / pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / prieſtes / officers / and ſtraungers within the couenaunt of the Lorde. Then what God requireth of one (as touching this leage) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of all / for hys iuſtice is immutable / &amp; what he dampneth in anye one that he muſte dampne in others / for he is righteous without parcialitie. Then let vs conſider what God hath requyred of ſuche as hathe bene in leage with hym / and what he pronounceth dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble.<note place="margin">Deu. xiij</note> Moyſes the mouth of God to his people of Iſrael ſpeaketh as foloweth: Yf thy brother the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of thy mother / or the wyfe of thy own boſome / or thy neyghbour / whom thou loueſt as thy own lyfe / ſhal priuely ſolyſt the / <hi>Sayng let vs go and ſerue other Goddes,</hi> whome thou haſt not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. Obey hym not / hear hym not / neither yet let thy eye ſpare hym / be not merciful vnto hym / nor hyde him not / but kyll hym / let thy hand be the fyrſt vpon hym / that ſuche a one maye be kylled / and then the handes of the holy people ſtone hym with ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / vntil he dye. And likewiſe commaundeth he to be donne with a hole citie / if the indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers therof turne backe to Idolatrie / addinge alſo / that the citie and the whole ſpoyle therof ſhalbe brent. That no portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe ſaued / nor yet that the citie ſhalbe buylded foreuer again becauſe it is accurſed of God.</p>
                  <p>Here is a playne declaracion / what God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth
<pb facs="tcp:8582:16"/>
of them that wil continew in leage with him / and what he hath dampned by his expreſt wordes. And do we eſteme (beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren) that the immutable God will wincke at our Idolatrie / as that he ſaw it not: ſeing he commaundeth iudgement to be executed ſo ſeuerly againſt Idolators / and againſte ſuche as onely prouoked or ſoliſted others to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie / that neither ſhould blood nor affinitie neither multitude nor ryches / ſaue ſuche as offendeth / neither yet that we ſhould cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayll their offences / but that we ſhould be the fyrſt that ſhould accuſe brother / ſonne / doughter / or wyfe / and why? becauſe he entendeth (ſaith Moyſes) to bring the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lorde thy God / Who led thy furth from the land of Egipte / and therfore let hym dye / that all Iſrael hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring / maye feare / and preſumed not after too commit the lyke abhomination. Let nothing apertayninge to ſuche a man or citie / cleaue vnto thy hande / that the Lord may turn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the furor of his wrath &amp; be moued ouer thy with moſt tender mercy and affeccion / and that he maye multiplye thy / as he hathe ſworne vnto thy fathers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Vvliij Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie is too be eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vved. &amp; the mainteners therof.</note>In theſe wordes moſt euidently is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto vs / why God wil that we auoide all felowſhip with Idolatrie / &amp; with the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the ſame: In whiche are thre thinges chiefly to be noted / fyrſte that the holy Ghoſt inſtruct vs / that maintaynours of Idolatrie / &amp; prouokers to the ſame / inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to draw vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God / &amp; therfore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vs / that we ſhal not cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail their i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pietie / but that we ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:8582:16"/>
make it knowen / &amp; that we ſhall puniſhe it / if we will haue the leage betwixte vs &amp; God too ſtande ſure. And here is the firmamente of my fyrſt cauſe / why / it is neceſſary to auoyde Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrie / becauſe that otherwiſe we declare oure ſelfes litell to regard / yea / to haue broken / and plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly denied that holy leage / which is betwen vs &amp; God / through Chriſt Ieſus. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darely it is to be noted / that Idolatrie ſo kindleth the wrath of God / that it is neuer quenched / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the offendors / &amp; all that they poſes / be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth / &amp; that by fyre. It may ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare that this is ſeueare &amp; rygorous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / but let the cauſe be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered / &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / that in the ſame / God ſheweth vnto vs his moſt ſinguler loue / declaring him ſelfe enemye vnto oure enemies / for all thoſe that wold draw vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God (be the kynges or quenes) bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the diuels nature / <note place="margin">Dravvers of men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God are of the deuils nature.</note> are enemies vnto God / &amp; therfore wil God that in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes / we declare our ſelfes enemies vnto them. And laſt it is to be noted / that obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God / in taking ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Idolatours / by ſuche meanes / as God hath appointed / is a cauſe why God ſheweth his mercye / why he multiplieth vs / &amp; enbraſeth vs with brotherly loue / where co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary wyſe / by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſentinge with Idolatrye / are the mercies of God ſhut vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs / &amp; are cutted of the bodie of Chriſt / to wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and roote / as trees withoute moyſture. But nowe ſhall ſome demaunde / what then? ſhall we go too / and kyll all Idolatours.<note place="margin">Queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere</note> That were the office &amp; dutye of euery ciuell magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate within hys realme and Iuriſdiccion.
<pb facs="tcp:8582:17"/>
But of you is requyred only to auoyd partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacion and company of that abhominacion / as wel in body as in ſoule / as Dauid and Paule plainly teacheth.<note place="margin">Pſal. xvi</note> Dauid in his exile / in the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of Idolatours ſayth: <hi>I will not offer their drinke offeringes of bloud, neyther yet will I take their name into my mouthe, &amp; Paule ſayth:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. x.</note> 
                     <hi>You maye not be partakers of the Lordes table, and of the table of deuils,</hi> you may not drinke the Lordes cup / and the cup of deuils. As theſe two places / of ſcriptur plainly reſolueth the former queſtion / ſo do they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that which is before ſayd. That the leag betwixt vs and God requireth / auoydinge off all Idolatrye.<note place="margin">1. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xxvij.</note> Fyrſt playne it is / that in Gathe and in Corinthus / were no ſmal number off Idolatours / when Dauid was there in exile / &amp; when Paule wrote hys Epiſtle / yet neither ſayth Dauid / that he wil kyl any in that place becauſe he was their magiſtrate / neither ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth Paule any ſuche commaundement / but in one thing they both agre / that ſuche as hath ſocitie &amp; leage with God / muſt ſo abhorre Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrye / that no parte of the bodye be defyled therwith. <hi>For Dauid ſayeth: I will not take their names in my mouth.</hi> As he wolde ſaye / ſo odious are the names of falſe &amp; vaine God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / that the mencion of them is righteouſlye compared to ſtinckinge donge / &amp; vile carion / whiche neither can be eaten / neither yet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid without diſpleaſur of ſuche that hath not loſt the iudgemente of their ſences / &amp; therfore ſayeth Dauid / I wil not defyle me mouth with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that is / I wil neuer ſpeake one fauorable
<pb facs="tcp:8582:17"/>
worde of them. I thinke much leſſe / wolde he haue croched and kneled before them for anye mans pleaſure. Aduert brethren / <note place="margin">Shyfte makers are dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blers.</note> that Dauid inſpyred with the holy Ghoſte knew no ſuch ſheftes / as worldly wyſe men imagyn nowe a dayes: That they maye kept their hartes pure and cleane to God / howbeit / their body dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe with the diuel: <hi>Not ſo deare brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not ſo,</hi> The temple of God hath nothing to do with Idols. The cauſe expreſſeth Dauid in their wordes: <hi>The Lorde hym ſelfe is my portion and my enheritaunce.</hi> Greate is the cauſe / yf it be deaply conſidered. Dauid illuminated by the holy Ghoſt ſeyth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſelfe ſame thing / which before we haue aleaged of the Apoſtles wordes / that God will not parte ſpoyle with the deuil / promitting hym to haue the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the body / &amp; he too ſtande contente with the ſoule / harte and mynde. No brethren / Dauid marketh this / the fundament &amp; reaſon / why / he wil neither offer ſacrefice to Idols / neither yet defyle hys mouthe with their names / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſayeth he) <hi>the Lorde is my porcion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vvhat the leage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvvene vs and God re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quireth.</note> as he wolde ſaye / ſuche is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the leage betwene me and my God / that as he is my to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of defence againſt my enemies / preſeruing and noriſhing bothe the body &amp; ſoule / ſo muſte I be hole his in bodye and ſoule / for my God is of that nature / that he will ſuffer no portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys glory to be geuen to another. In confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this ſayeth Eſay / <note place="margin">Eſai. 57.</note> after he had rebu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked their Idols and vayne inuecinons. <hi>Theſe are thy porcion, and Ieremy likewiſe,</hi> in moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth / let thy bedfellowes deliuer
<pb facs="tcp:8582:18"/>
thy / call vpon them / and let them heare thy / thou haſt committed fornicacion &amp; whordome with ſtocke and ſtone.<note place="margin">Ierem. 3.</note> The prophetes meaning thereby / that Idolators can haue no leage nor couenaunt with God / in ſo farre / that their hartes be alyenated from hym / which the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of their bodies doth teſtefye / and therfore renounceth God ſuche leage / &amp; bounde as was before offered for Eſay wolde ſaye / euen ſuche as thou haſt choſen / ſuche ſhalbe the portion. And Ieremye wolde ſay / thou put thy truſt to them / which he meaneth / by the lye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in bed / &amp; therfore let them ſhewe their power in thy deliueraunce / and thus he ſendeth them as it were to ſucke water from hote burninge coles.<note place="margin">Note wel</note> It ſhall nothing excuſe / to ſaye we truſt not in Idols / for ſo will euery Idolatour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage / but if either you or they in Gods honor / do any thing contrary to Gods woorde / you ſhew your ſelfe to put your truſt / in ſomwhat els beſydes God / and ſo are you Idolatours. Marke brethren / <note place="margin">Truſting in mans vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrie.</note> that many maketh an Idoll of their owne wiſedom or fantaſye / more tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to that / which they thinke good / nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God / who plainly ſayeth not that thinge / which ſeameth good in thy eyes / do vnto thy God / but what thy Lord God hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded them. But of this ſome other tyme / God willing / more ſhalbe ſpoken herof / I ſuppoſe it be plaine / that lyke as God is immutable / who / by his law / hath not only forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with Idolators in their Idolatrie / but alſo hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb facs="tcp:8582:18"/>
be taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And as the ſaintes of God were inſpired with the holye ghoſte / who wolde not ſo much as ones fauourablye ſpeake of Idols / <note place="margin">Marke.</note> &amp; laſte as the ſcriptures be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallable / which promiſeth that God maye not abyde / that our bodies ſerue the deuill / in ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our bodies with Idolatrie / ſo is it off more neceſſitie / that both in bodye &amp; ſoule / we abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſame / yf we wil haue the leage betwene God &amp; vs to ſtande ſure. I will not troble this tyme with au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwering to any ſuch obiections / as men ſekinge to leue as they liſte / dothe now a daies inuent / ſeing that partely in another letter: I haue au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered theſame / &amp; yf God ſhal grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t any reſt in this wicked world / I purpoſe by the grace of God / as occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be offered fully to aunſwere what can be ſayd for their defence / whiche in very dede / when all is ſayde that they can / they haue ſayde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that God will admit.<note place="margin">By frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, men ſhevv them ſelf to haue no faith.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now reſtith to ſhew that in haunting Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie / we declare oure ſelfes too be withoute fayth / and dothe denye to beare witneſſe vnto God / but that fayth purgeth the hart / I truſt none of you will denye. But whether that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde fayth requyreth an eternal confeſſion / and yf a man maye not haue faythe / and yet doo in ceremonies of the Churche / as the worlde dothe / herein perchaunce you doubte. As too the fyrſte the Apoſtle aunſwereth in theſe woordes / <note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> in the harte it is beleued vnto Iuſtice / but by the mouthe is confeſſion vnto ſaluacion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8582:19"/>And Dauid ſayth: I haue beleued / &amp; therefore I haue ſpoken / but I was ſore trobled / as Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid wolde ſaye / I wolde not counſaile the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion of my faith / howbeit / troble did enſew theſame. Thus the holy Ghoſt ioyneth fayth and confeſſion / as thinges that be inſeperable the one from the other / and therefore dare I not take vpon me to diſceauer them / but muſte ſaye / that where trew faith is / there is alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion of the ſame / <note place="margin">Note wel</note> when tyme and neceſſitie requireth / &amp; that where confeſſion is not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that their faithe is a ſlepe / if we be not frome home.</p>
                  <p>Now is it to be conſidered / if this tyme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth the confeſſion of our faith.<note place="margin">Vvhether this tyme re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quireth con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our faith.</note> Chriſt and his Euangile are oppugned / his holye ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes are prophaned. Chriſtes meſſengers are ſome exiled / ſome cruelly tormented in pryſon / our aduerſaries hath gotten the vpperhande / and an execrable Idol / <note place="margin">the maſſe</note> erected vp in confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all iniquitie. What now ſhall I do? that am aſſured that all this is abhominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / here Chriſt is in battaile / ſhal I do as the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude / or as Chriſtes enemies doth / what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion geue I then? Aſſuredly euen ſuch as the reſt doeth / for neither doeth foote / hande / eye / nor mouth witnes the contrary.<note place="margin">Note.</note> The feete ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the bodye to ſerue an Idoll. The eye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth it with a certayn reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. The mouth dare not whiſper what the hart thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth / yea / the handes are extended / and geueth ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of humble obedience. Haue I not nowe iuſtefied the deuell / and damned Chriſt? it can not be denyed. But let me haue no credit / one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:8582:19"/>
theſame be yet proued by moſte plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of Gods ſacred ſcripture. The Lord by hys prophete Eſaye / ſayeth his people of Iſrael / and this is aunſwer alſo to the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d queſtion / yf I may not do as the worlde doth / and yet haue faithe / <hi>You are my witneſſes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſai 44.</note> whether there be anye God but I alone / is there any creator that I ſhould not know him Theſe woordes were ſpoken / as it were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an entreſſe too rebuke all Idolatrie &amp; the vaine inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tours of the ſame / as the Lord wold ſaye. Thou houſe of Iacob / and your naturall chyldren / diſcending from Abraham. You are my people / whom peculiarly I haue choſen to ſhew in you the greatnes of my name / and for that ende haue I ſpoken vnto you / hidde thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges from the beginning / that you may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande and knowe that there is no knowlege but in me alone / that you perſwaded of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finet wiſedome / power and goodnes may teſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye / and beare witnes of theſame / too ſuche as hath not then lyke vnderſtanding with you. Hereof it is playne / that of ſuche as to whom God geueth knowlege / he requireth a confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to prouoke the ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to embrace God and his worde / or at leaſt that by the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding man / the vanitie of the foliſhe ſhoulde be rebuked. So zelous is God ouer hys giftes / that yf we labour not to employe them to the glorie of God / and to proffit of others his crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours / he will according to the threatning of Chriſt / take the talent from vs / and will geue it to ſuche as will labor there vppon. Some perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wolde gladly labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> / but theyſe not
<pb facs="tcp:8582:20"/>
what frute ſhall ſuccede / &amp; therfore iudge they better to ceaſe. Euen as God could bring forth no fruite / except he make vs fyrſt of counſaile. God is to be obeyed in his commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and the ſucceſſe is to be committed to him / whoſe wiſedome is vnſearcheable / he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth vs refraine Idolatrie / to let other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee that thei do wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.<note place="margin">Vvhy vve ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine from Idolatrie.</note> This ought we obey / albeit the preſent death ſhould folow / for we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as witnes betwene God &amp; the blind world / as is beforeſaid: Iſrael thou arte my witnes. The world aſketh / <note place="margin">Note.</note> is the mans Gods ſeruice / or is it Idolatrie? God hath opened to vs / that it is abhominable Idolatrie / but when that we for feare of our vyle carkaſes / <note place="margin">The maſſe is abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</note> do as the blinde world doth. What witnes beare we? Aſſuredly falſe witnes againſt God / for that we iuſtefye and mayntaine that with our preſence / which God condemneth againſt our neyghbour / for that we confirme hym in errour to bothe our condemnacions. But when we abſtaye from all felowſhip of Idolatrie / what euer enſewe there vpon / we do our dueties vnto Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie. Let no man thinke that I am more ſeuear then neceſſitie requireth. No brethren / I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes contein my affirmations / within the boundes of Gods ſcriptures / and that ſhal Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie the prophet witnes / who writing to the Iewes / being pryſoners in Babylon / after he had forbidden them to folowe the vaine rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of that people / amongeſt whome they wexe then conuerſant by many reaſons / pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge that their Idols were no Goddes / at
<pb facs="tcp:8582:20"/>
laſte he ſayth / you ſhall ſaye to them:<note place="margin">Ierem. 10</note> 
                     <hi>The Goddes that made neither heauen neither earthe,</hi> ſhall periſh from the earthe / and from vnder the heauen. Here is to be obſerued / as Ihon Caluine / that ſingular inſtrumente off God moſte diligently noteth.</p>
                  <p>That the reſte of the prophetes worke was written in the Hebrew tounge / <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Idols &amp; that chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginge their natural to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</note> whiche then was peculiar to the Iewes / but theſe verſes and woordes aboue reherſed / were written in the Caldee tounge / in the tounge of that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / when the Iewes were then in thraldome as that the prophet woulde conſtrein them to chaunge their naturall tounge / and in plaine woordes declare the hatered and alienation / whiche they had from all worſhippynge off Idols. I beſeche you brethren / marke the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the prophete / he ſayeth not / you maye thinke in your hartes / that they are vayne / &amp; that they ſhall periſhe / but you ſhall ſaye it / &amp; that not preuely / but to them / who putte their truſte in ſuche vanitie / as that the thre chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren openly ſpake / denyenge to geue the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their bodies before an Idoll. And Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel that wolde not kepe ſecrete the confeſſion of hys fayth onely thyrty dayes / as in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer letter more plainely is expreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d / hereof it is playne that requyringe that you prophaine not your bodyes with Idolatrie. I requyre no more then Goddes ſcriptures by plaine precep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples teacheth. Neither yet requyre I of euery man / and at all tymes ſo muche. For I conſtrai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne no man to go to Idolators / 
<pb facs="tcp:8582:21"/>
in the tyme of their Idolatrie / and to ſay that all that they do / is abhominable and naughte. But onely that we kepe our owne bodyes (cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led of the Apoſtle the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the holy Ghoſt)<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> cleane from all ſuch diabolicall conuencions / which that we do is moſt profitable / and alſo neceſſary to the preſeruation of our ſelfes / and of our poſteritie / of whome ſomwhat (now at thende) muſt I ſpeake.</p>
                  <p>Euery man that is not degenerated too the nature of a brute beaſte / will appeare to beare ſuche loue to his chyldren / that to leaue them riche / in reſt / and in good ſtate / he pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly will ſuffer troubles / and without grudge will doo many thinges / that otherwiſe are contrary to hys owne pleaſure. And with my hart I wiſh to God / that the perfection of this were more deaply grounded in mans hart / I meane very loue / <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13</note> &amp; not fonde foliſhnes / whiche vnder the name of loue / procureth deſtruction of bodye and ſoule / where co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe / trew loue moſt carefully laboureth for ſaluation of bothe / yf this loue I ſaye / towardes our chyldren / which euery man pretendeth to haue / be in vs. Then of neceſſitie it is / that for theſe cauſes we ſhall aduoid all ſocietie of thoſe fylthye abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This my affeccion may apeare ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge but if it be with indifferencye perceaued / it ſhalbe very eaſy to be vnderſtande.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Note ye fathers.</note>The onely way to leaue our chyldren bleſſed and happy is to leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> righteouſly inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Gods trew religion / for what auayleth all that is in earth / <note place="margin">Note.</note> if conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacion folow death yea / &amp; Goddes vengeaunce goo before theſame
<pb facs="tcp:8582:21"/>
as of neceſſitie they muſte / where the trewe knowlege of God is abſent.<note place="margin">The trevv knovvlege of god is not borne vvith man.</note> Playne it is / that the trew knowlege of God is not borne wyth man / neither yet commeth vnto him with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall power / but he muſt haue ſcoolemaſters to trayne hym vp in that / whiche he lacketh / <hi>The chief ſcholemayſter,</hi> (the holy Ghoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) of the age folowing / is the worke prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies &amp; lief of the forefathers / where vnto com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monly we ſe the chyldren ſo addict &amp; bound / &amp; eſpecially / if it be in Idolatrie. That God cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng by the mouthes of his meſſingers / haue muche to do / to ryffe or plucke any man backe from their forefathers footeſteppes.</p>
                  <p>Now if that you altogether refuſinge / <note place="margin">Note and deſpiſe not.</note> God ſtoupe vnder Idolatrie / what ſchoolemaiſters are you to your poſteritie / what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mage ſhewe you to your chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Yea / in what eſtate leaue you them / bothe touching bodye &amp; ſoule.<note place="margin">3. Reg. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly / you are euen ſuche ſcholemaiſters / as were thoſe fathers / who conſentinge to Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam / to his Idolatrie left vnto their chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a patrone of perdicion. To ſpeake it plainly / you leaue them blynded in Idolatrie / &amp; bound ſlaues to the deuell without hope of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or light to be receaued.<note place="margin">Euaſ you Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere</note> Tuſſhe wilſome ſaye. The Lord knoweth his owne: Trewe it is. But this ordenary meanes to come by hys knowledge / are not to contempned. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth you to teache your chyldren his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / ſtatutes and ceremonies. That they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe maye teache the ſame to the generations folowing. But yet will ſome obiecte / what taught our fathers vnto vs? O deare breathre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8582:22"/>
be not ſo ingrate and vnthankefull vnto god. Neither yet I wolde that you ſhoulde flatter your ſelfes / thinking that ſuche a tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet ſhall be blowen to your poſteritie / as hath bene blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto you.<note place="margin">Let the rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande.</note> Yf all come to ſo cloſe ſylence / as che Lordes meſſengers fonde the beginning of this our age. When this hole realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de was drouned in ſo deadly a ſlepe / that the ſounde of the Lordes trompet was not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande / while fyrſte the moſte parte of the blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers gaue their bloude in a teſtimonie / that their doctrine was the ſame / which bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with bloud / was planted and kept in mynde by the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame / and by bloud encreaſed / and did fructe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye / will the Lord haue his meſſengers to fight alone?<note place="margin">Note.</note> will he beſtowe ſuche abundaunce off bloude vpon your chyldren / to encorage them / as that he did vpon you / for your inſtruction &amp; encoragement / yf that ye all ſo traytorouſly fle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym / in the daye of this his battaile. The contrary is greatly to be feared. Oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoluinge howe God hath vſed my tounge (my tounge I ſay / being moſt wretched of others) plainly to ſpeake the trobles that are perfet. There occurreth to my mynde a certein admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicion / that God wolde / I commonly ſhoulde vſe in all congregations. The admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was this / that the laſte trompet was in blowynge within the realme of Englande / and therfore ought euery man to prepare him for battaile / for if the trompet ſhould ceaſe / and be put too ſylence / then ſhoulde it neuer agayne blowe with lyke force in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / tyll the comming of the Lorde Ieſus. O deare brethren / howe
<pb facs="tcp:8582:22"/>
ſore theſe threatninges perſeth my owne hart this daye / onely God knoweth / &amp; in what ago<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye of harte I wryte this ſame / God ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare / when the ſecretes of all hartes ſhalbe diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cloſed. I wyſhe my ſelfe to be accurſed of God / as touching all earthly pleaſure or comforte for one yeare of that tyme / which (alas) ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you nor I dyd righteouſly eſteme / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all abounded with vs. I ſob and grone / I cal and I praye / that in that point I may be deceaued. But I am commaunded to ſtande content / for it is God hym ſelf / that perfourmeth the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of his trew meſſengers / hys iuſtice &amp; order can not be peruerted. The ſunne kepeth hys ordenary courſe / and leapeth not backe frome the Weſt to the South / but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it goith doun we lacke the light of it tyl it ryſe the next day towards the Eaſt again. And ſo is it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th the light of the goſpel / which hath his day apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God / <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.</note> as witneſſeth Chriſt ſaying while ye haue the light / beleue in the light / that dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you not.<note place="margin">Rom. 13. Heb. 3.</note> And Paul / the night is paſſed / &amp; the day is come (meani<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel) &amp; alſo this day / yf you heare his voice har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den not your hartes. And albeit that this daye be all tyme fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtes incarnacion / tyll his laſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming again.<note place="margin">Note.</note> Yet euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it is / that all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hath not had at one ſiene the light of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde. But by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it is / that where the light of the goſpell for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes / hath ben take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away / there is it not to this day yet reſtored again / witnes hole Iſrael / &amp; all the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the gentylles where Chriſt was firſt preached by thapoſtels.
<pb facs="tcp:8582:23"/>
What is in Aſya? ignoraunce of God / what in Affrika?<note place="margin">Examples of gods ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geaunce: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kefulnes.</note> abnegation of Chriſte / what in thoſe moſt notable Churches of the Grecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / wher Chriſt was planted by Paule &amp; long after / vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by others? Mahomet and his falſe ſecte / Yea / what is in Rome? the moſt Idol of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers / that aduerſary to Chriſte / that man of ſynne extolled aboue all that is called God. Hath God puniſſhed thoſe natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s before vs / not onely the firſt offendors / but euen their po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteritie to this day / &amp; ſhal he ſpare vs? yf we be lyke vnthankefull as they were / yea / if we be worſe then they were? for of them no ſmal nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſuffered perſecution / baniſhment / ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / pouertye / &amp; fynally the death for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt / who hauing only this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge / that Idols were odious before God / could neither for loſe of temporal goodes / for honours offered if they wolde obeye / nor yet for moſt cruel tormentes ſuffered in reſiſting ones be perſwaded to bowe before Idols. And (alas) ſhal we after ſo many graces that God hath offered vnto vs for pleaſure / or for vaine threatning of thoſe / whom your hartes kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth / &amp; your mouthes hath confeſſed to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Idolatours / ronne backe to Idolatrie / to the perdicion of your ſelfes / &amp; of your poſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie to come. Shall goddes holy preceptes worke no greater obedience in you? ſhall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur no otherwiſe mollifye your hartes? ſhall not fatherly pitie ouercome that cruelnes. O behold your chyldern / and conſider thende of their creation / greate crueltie it were to ſaue your ſelfes / &amp; to dampne them. But o more
<pb facs="tcp:8582:23"/>
then crueltie and madnes / that can not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed / yf for the pleaſure of a momente / you depriued your ſelfe / &amp; your poſteritie of that eternall ioye / that is ordeyned for thoſe that continueth in confeſſion of Chriſtes name / &amp; truthe to the ende / which aſſuredly you do / yf without reſiſtaunce al together / you retorne to Idolatrie againe.<note place="margin">Note.</note> Alas / then the trompet hath loſt the ſound / the ſunne is gone doune / and the light vaniſhed / but &amp; if that God ſhall ſtrengthen you / boldely to withſtand all ſuche impietie / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is their but a darke myſtie cloude ouerſpred the ſunne for a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / which ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſhall vaniſhe / ſo that the beames of the ſunne / afterward ſhalbe ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>folde more bright and amyable then they were before. Your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience &amp; conſtauncie ſhalbe the lowdar trom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet to your poſteritie / <note place="margin">god graunt you may vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtande.</note> then were all the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the prophetes that cryed vnto you / and therfore for the tendre mercye of God. Arme your ſelfe to ſtand with Chriſt / Flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that abhominable Idol. The mayntaynors therof ſhall not eſcape the vengeaunce of God. Let it be knowen to your poſteritie / that you were Chriſtians / and no Idolatours / and ſo is not the trompet ceaſed ſo longe as any boldely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth Idolatrie.<note place="margin">The obſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the fleſhe. <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </note> Theſe preceptes are ſharpe &amp; harde to be obſerued will ſome obiect. And yet agayn I affirme that / compared with the plagues / which aſſuredly ſhal fal vpon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempnours / they ſhalbe founde eaſye &amp; light for auoyding Idolatrie / <note place="margin">Note this Antitheſis, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider it vvel.</note> it maye chaunce that you be contempned in the world / but obeyers of Idolatrie / as before God thei are abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb facs="tcp:8582:24"/>
/ ſo ſhall they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled body &amp; ſoule to burne in hell / for auoyding of Idolatrie / your worldly ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhalbe ſpoyled / but for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng Idolatrie / heauenly ryches ſhalbe loſt for auoyding Idolatrie / you maye fall in the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of earthly tyrauntes / but obeyers / conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and mayntaynors of Idolatrie ſhall not eſcape the handes of the liuing God / for auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Idolatrie / your chyldern ſhalbe depriued of father / frendes / ryches / &amp; earthly reſt / but by obeyeng Idolatrie / they ſhalbe left without God without the knowlege of his worde / and without the hope of his kyngdome.</p>
                  <p>Conſider deare brethren / that how muche more dolerous it is to be torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in hel / then to ſuffer troble in earth / to be depriued of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly ioye / then to be robbed of tranſitory ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches. To fall in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of the lyuing God / then to abyde mans vayne / &amp; vncertein diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. So muche more fearfull &amp; daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous it is / to obey Idolatrie or diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent too that abhomination / then auoydinge the ſame / to ſuffer what inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low therupon by mans tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny. O be not like to Eſau / that ſolde and loſt his byrthright for a meaſe of potage. I am not preiudiciall too Gods mercies / as that ſuche as after ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent / ſhall not fynd grace. God forbidde / for here in am I moſt aſſuredly perſwaded. That in what ſo euer houre a ſynner ſhall repente / God ſhall not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber one of hys iniquities / but albeit / his offences were as redde as Skar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lette / they ſhall be made as whyte as ſnowe.<note place="margin">ze. 18.33</note> And albeit in multitude they paſſed number / 
<pb facs="tcp:8582:24"/>
yet ſo ſhall they be blotted out / that none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall appeare to the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacion of the very repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tant / for hys promiſes be infallible / <note place="margin">Eſai. 1.</note> that ſuche as truly beleue in Chriſt / ſhall neuer entre in to iudgement / for the bloud of Chriſte Ieſus / <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.5</note> purgeth them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſynne / ſo that how farre the heauen is dyſtant from the earth / ſo farre doth he remoue the ſynnes from the penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>But conſider dearly beloued brethren,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.</note> that theſe and lyke promiſies are made to penitent ſinners / &amp; dothe nothing apertaininge to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaine parſons / Idolatours / <note place="margin">The confu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of God are made to penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners onely.</note> nor too fearfull ſhrinkers from the truthe / for feare of worldly troble. And yf any alleage / God may cal them to repentaunce / how wicked that any man be. I aunſwere that I acknowlege / and doth cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Gods omnipotenſye / to be ſo free / that he maye do what pleaſeth hys wyſedom / but yet is he not bounde to do / all that our fanteſie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth.<note place="margin">Note.</note> And likewiſe I know that God is ſo louing and ſo kinde / to ſuche as feareth hym / that he will performe their willes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures / although kynges &amp; princes had ſworne to the contrary. But herein ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the doubt whether that ſuche as for pleaſure of men / or for auoydinge tempo all puniſhment / defyleth them ſelfes with Idolatrie. Feareth God / and whether they with all their lyues / denyeth Chriſt by conſentinge to Idolatrie / ſhal at the laſte houre / be called to repentaunce. No ſuche promeſe haue we within the ſcriptures of god but rather the expreſt contrarie. And therfore God is not to be tempted / but is too be harde / feared and obeyed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8582:25"/>When thus earneſtly he calleth &amp; threatneth not withoute cauſe.<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> Paſſe from the middeſt of her / o my people (ſaith the Lorde) that you be not partakers of her plagues / and that is ment of that abhominable whore / and of her abhomination.<note place="margin">3. Reg 18 1. Cor. 10 Math. 10</note> 
                     <hi>How long will you halte on bothe partes,</hi> you maye not bothe be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the cup of the Lorde / and of the cup of the deuel. He that denieth me before men / I will denye hym before my father / he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth not hym ſelfe / &amp; taketh vp hys croſſe &amp; folow me / is not worthy of me. No man put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his hande to the plough / &amp; lokinge back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde is worthie of the kyngdome of God. And Paule to the Hebrewes only meaneth of this ſynne / where he ſayeth:<note place="margin">heb. 6.10</note> who willinglye ſynneth after the knowledge of the trueth / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be renewed to repentaunce. O deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren / remember the dignitie of your vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / you haue folowed Chriſt / you haue proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med warre againſt Idolatrie / you haue laide hande vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trueth / and hath communicat at the Lordes table. Will you now ſodenlye ſlyde backe? will ye refuſe Chriſt &amp; his truth? and make paccion with the dyuell &amp; with his deceauable doctrine? Will ye treade the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud of his teſtament vnder your fete / and ſet vp an Idoll before the people / whiche thinges aſſuredly you doo / as ofte as euer you preſent your bodies amongſt Idolatours / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that blaſphemous Idoll. God the father of all mercies for Chriſt his ſonnes ſake pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue you from that ſore temptation / whoſe dolours and daungers / very ſorowe will not
<pb facs="tcp:8582:25"/>
ſuffer me to expreſſe. Alas brethren / it is to be feared / that if you fall once a ſlepe / you lye to long before you be wakened.<note place="margin">Note.</note> Yet ſome ſhall obiect / Peter the Denyar obteyned mercye.<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betvven Peter &amp; our diſſembling goſpelers.</note> To whome I aunſwer particular examples / maketh no common law / neither yet is there any reſemblance or lykelyhodde betwene the fall of Peter / and our daily Idolatrie. Peter vpon a ſodayn / without any former purpoſe / thus denyed Chriſte within the ſpace of a houre or two. We vpon determined purpoſe / and aduiſed mynde dayly deny Chriſt. Peter had Chriſtes aſſurance and promyſe / that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hys deniall he ſhould be conuerted. We haue Chriſtes threatninges / that if we denye we ſhalbe denyed. Peter in the biſhops hall / and amongſt wicked men of warre / commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hys offence for feare of lyfe. We in oure citie and houſholde / onely for the looſe of the wicked Mammon / dothe no leſſe. Peter at the warninge of the Cocke / and at Chriſtes looke / left that companye / that prouoked hys ſynne. We after Chriſtes admonitions yea / after gentle exhortations / and fearfull threat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninges / will continew in the middeſt of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latours / and for their pleaſures will crocke &amp; knele / as the deuel commaundeth / what lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhode is here / let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge. But much I wonder / that men that can eſpye ſo narow thiftes / as to hyde them ſelfes frome the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens of God / behynde a buſſhe with Adam their father / can not alſo eſpye that Iudas was an Apoſtle in preſens of men / of no les
<pb facs="tcp:8582:26"/>
auctoritie then Peter was / that Cayn was the fyrſt borne in the world.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 10</note> That Saule was the firſt anoynted king by Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment / and by his prophete / and that Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel was a man of moſte ſingular wyſedom / and yet none of theſe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d place of repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.<note place="margin">2. Reg. 16</note> Haue we any other aſſuraunces and particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler warrantes within the ſcriptures of God / then they had that all our lyfe we maye be in leage with the deuell / <note place="margin">Note.</note> and then at oure plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that we maye laye hande vppon Chriſte / and clothe vs with hys iuſtice:<note place="margin">Ioel. 2. Rom. 10. 2. timo. 2</note> 
                     <hi>Be not decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued brethren,</hi> for albeit moſte / trewe it is / that who ſoo euer incalleth the name of the Lorde / ſhalbe ſaued / Yet lyke trew it is / that whoſoeuer incalleth the name of the Lorde / ſhall auoyde and eſſchewe all iniquitie / &amp; that whoſoeuer contine with in open iniquitie / the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame man incalleth not the name of the Lord / neither hath God any reſpecte to hys prayer / <note place="margin">Ioh. 9. Ioh. 38. The maſſe the deuels ſacrament and ſeale.</note> and greater iniquitie was neuer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge of the worlde / then is contayned in that abhominable Idoll / for it is the ſeale off that leage / whiche the deuell hath made with the peſtilent ſonnes of Antechriſte / and is the very chief cauſe / why the bloud of the ſainctes of God / hath ben ſhed nere the ſpace of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeare / for ſo longe almoſt hath it bene in deuiſing / and in deckinge with that whoriſhe garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / <note place="margin">The longe parching of the popiſſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>aſſe.</note> wherein it now triumpheth / againſt Chriſt / againſte the onely one ſacrifice of hys death / &amp; merites of hys paſſion / which whole abhomination you confirme / and ſheweth
<pb facs="tcp:8582:26"/>
youre ſelfes / conſentinge to the murther of thoſe that hath ſuffered for ſpeaking againſte it / as oft as euer you decore that Idoll wyth your preſens.<note place="margin">Note.</note> And therfore auoyde it / as that ye will be partakers with Chriſt / with whom ye haue ſworne to dye and to lyue in baptiſme and in his holye ſupper. Shame it were to breake promys vnto man / but is it not more ſhame too breake it vnto God? fooliſhnes it were to leaue that kynge / whoſe victorie you did ſe preſente / and too take parte with hym / whome vnderſtode &amp; perceaued to be ſo van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſhed and ouerthrowen / that he neither might withſtande / neither yet abyde the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of his aduerſarie.<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.16</note> O brethren / is not the deuel the prince of this worlde / vanquiſhed &amp; caſt out? hath not Chriſte made conqueſte off hym? hath he not caryed our ſelfe vp to glorie in diſpite of ſathans malice.<note place="margin">Acto. 1.</note> Shall not oure champion retorne? you vnderſtande that he ſhall and that with expedition / when ſathan and his adherentes Idolatours / <note place="margin">Apo. 20.</note> worſhippers of that blaſphemous beaſt / fylthie perſonnes / and fearefull ſhrinkers frome the truthe of God ſhalbe caſte in the lake burninge fyre and brimſtone / which neuer ſhalbe quenched.<note place="margin">Foliſhe feare.</note> But in the meane tyme / you feare corporall death / yf nature admitted any man too lyue euer / then had your feare ſome apare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon / but yf corporall death be common to all / why will you leoperde to leſe the lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge? to decline and eſcape / that whiche ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ryche / neither poore / neither wyfe / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:8582:27"/>
fooliſhe / proude of ſtomake / nor feable of coraige / and fynally no earthly creature / by no craft nor mene of man did euer eſcape / yf any hath eſcaped the horrible feare of deathe / it was ſuche as boldely did withſtande mennes iniquitie in the earthe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The fleſhe can doo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but grudge.</note>
                     <hi>But it grudgeth the fleſſhe</hi> (ſaye you) for feare of the torment / let it do the owne nature and office / for ſo muſt it do tyll it be burdened with Chriſtes croſſe / and then no doubte / ſhall God ſende ſuche comforte / as now we looke not for. Let vs not torne backe from Chriſte / albeit the fleſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine / and feareth the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wonder it is that the waye too lyfe is ſo fearfull vnto vs, conſidering that ſo greate a number of our brethren / hath paſſed before vs in at the ſame gatte / that we ſo muche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre. Hath not the moſte parte of the ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of God entred in to their reſt / by tormente &amp; trobles of whome witneſſeth Paule / ſome were racked / <note place="margin">Others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs hath paſt to lyfe by torment.</note> ſome heawin a ſonder / ſome ſlayne with ſwerdes / ſome walked vp &amp; doun in ſhepe ſkinnes / <hi>in neade, tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> in mountaines / dennes / and in caues off the earthe / and in all thoſe extremities / what complaintes heare we of their mouthes / ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be that they lament the blindnes of the world / and the perdition of their perſecutors. Did God comforte them / and ſhall he deſpiſe vs yf in obediens to him / we folow their foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteppes / he ſhall not do it / for he hath promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the contrarye. <hi>And therfore dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lorde,</hi> As that you purpoſe too
<pb facs="tcp:8582:27"/>
auoyde the vengeaunce of God / that ſodenly ſhall ſtrike all obſtinate Idolatours. As that you wolde hane the leage betwene God and you to ſtande ſure / and as that you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare your ſelfes to haue true faith / withoute whiche no man euer ſhall entre in lyfe. And fynally / as that you wil leaue the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God / in poſſeſſion to youre chyldren. Auoyde Idolatrie / &amp; all participation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of / for it is ſo odious before Gods preſens / that not onely dothe he puniſhe the inuentours / and fyrſte offendours / but oftentymes theyr poſteritie are ſtryken with blindenes and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynes of mynde.<note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> The battaylle ſhall apeare ſtronge / which you are to ſuffer / but the Lord hym ſelfe ſhall be youre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte / he ſhall come in youre defence with hys mightie power / <note place="margin">Zacha. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Pſal 46.57.61.</note> he ſhall geue you vittorie / when none is hoped for / he ſhall tourne your teres to euerlaſtynge Ioye / he ſhall confounde your enemyes with the breath of hys mouthe / <note place="margin">Apoc. 7.22. Pſal. 55.</note> he ſhall ſet you ſe their deſtruction that now are moſt proude.</p>
                  <p>The God of all comforte &amp; conſolation for Chriſt Ieſus / his ſonnes ſake / grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that this ſimple &amp; plaine admonition / yea / rather the warning of the holy ghoſte maye be receaued / &amp; accepted of you with no les feare &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce then I haue written it vnto you with vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned loue / and ſorowfull hart / &amp; then I doubte not / but we ſhall be comforted / when all ſuche as now moteſteth vs / ſhall trymble &amp; ſhake by the comming of our Lord Ieſus / whoſe omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent ſprete perſerue and kepe you vndefiled bodye and ſoule to the ende. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:28"/>
                  <head>☞A godly prayer.</head>
                  <p>AH Lorde / moſte ſtronge and mightye God / which deſtroyeſt the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayles of the vngodly / and ryddeſt awai the tyrauntes of thys worlde / out of the earth at thy pleaſure / ſo that no counſaill or force ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſiſte thyne eternal counſaill and euerlaſting determination / we thyne poore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creatures and humble ſeruauntes / do moſte inſtantly deſyre the for the loue that thou haſt to thyne welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued / and onely begotten ſoune oure Lorde and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt / that thou wilt loke vpon thyne cauſe / for it is tyme o Lorde / and bringe to naught all thoſe thinges that are or ſhalbe apoynted / determined and fully agreed agaynſte the and thy holy woorde / let not the enemyes of thy trueth to miſerablye oppreſſe thy word &amp; thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / which ſeke thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie / tender the aduancement of thy pure reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion / &amp; aboue all thinges wiſhe in their hartes that thy holy name may onely be glorefied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge all nations. Geue vnto thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes the mouth of thy truthe &amp; wyſedom / whiche no man maye reſiſte: And althoughe we haue moſte iuſtly deſerued thys plague and famyn of thyne worde / yet vpon our trew repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / graunte we beſeke the / we maye be thereof releaſed / and here we promiſe before thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne maieſtie / better to vſe thy gyftes then we haue done / and more ſtrayghtlye to ordre oure
<pb facs="tcp:8582:28"/>
lyues / accordinge to thy holye will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure / and we will ſynge perpetuall prayſes too thy moſte bleſſed name / worldes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ende / throughe Ieſus Chriſte oure Lorde. Amen</p>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>FINIS.</hi>
                     <figure>
                        <head>GOD IS MY HELPER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:29"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:29"/>
                  <p>¶A confeſſion &amp; declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of praiers added ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto / by Ihon Knox / miniſter of chriſtes moſt ſacred Euangely / vpon the death of that moſte verteous and moſte famous king <hi>Edward the VI.</hi> kynge of Englande / Fraunce and Ireland / in whiche confeſſion / the ſayde Ihon doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe no leſſe hys owne offences / then the offences of others / to be the cauſe of the awaye takinge / of that moſte godly prince / nowe raininge with Chriſt whyle we abyde plagues for our vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
                  <p>¶Imprinted in Rome, before the Caſtel of ſ. Aungel / at the ſigne of ſainct Peter. In the moneth of Iuly / in the yeare of our Lorde. 1554. (?)</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:30"/>
                  <pb n="ij" facs="tcp:8582:30"/>
                  <head>A declaration of prayer / made by Ihon Knox.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the ſmall and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed flocke of Ieſus Chriſt / How neceſſary is the right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods name / other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called perfit prayer / beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth no chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to miſknow.<note place="margin">Prayer ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth out off true fayth. Rom. 10.</note> Seyng it is the very brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch / which ſprigeth forth of tru faith. Wherof / yf man be diſtitute / notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he be induid with whatſoeuer other vertues / yet in the preſens of God is he reputid for no Chriſtian / <note place="margin">Men negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praier are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in fayth.</note> therfore a manifeſt ſigne vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nothing of perfyt fayth / for yf the fyre may be without heate / or the burning lampe without lighte / then true fayth maye be without ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prayer. But becauſe in tymes paſſed was / and yet alas / within ſmal multitude is / that reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be prayer / whiche in the ſighte of God was and is nothing leſſe. I intende ſhortly too touch the circonſtaunce of prayer.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶What prayer is.</head>
                     <p>wHo wil praye / muſt knowe and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that praier is an eruſt &amp; familiar talking with God / to whom we declare our miſeries / whoſe ſupporte and helpe / we implore and deſyre in our aduerſities / &amp; whom we laude &amp; prayſe for our benefytes receiued.<note place="margin">Vvhat prayer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth.</note> So that prayer contayneth the expoſition of our dolours / the deſyre of Gods defence / and
<pb facs="tcp:8582:31"/>
louinge of his magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t name / as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of Dauid clearly teacheth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶What is to be obſerued in prayer.</head>
                     <p>THat this be moſt reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly done ſhould prouoke vs the conſideracion / in whoſe preſens we ſtande / to whome we ſpeke / and what we deſyre / ſtandinge in the preſence of the omnipotent creator of heauen &amp; earth / and of all the contentes therof / to whome aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt &amp; ſerue a thouſande thouſande of aungels / <note place="margin">Daniel. 3 Iob. 16.</note> geuing obedience to his eternal maieſtie / &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto hym / who knoweth the ſecretes off our hartes / diſſimulation &amp; lyes are alwayes odious / &amp; hated. And aſking that thing / which without we receiue of all other creators we are moſt miſerable / dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhould we atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that ſuche thinges as maye offende his godly preſence to the vttermoſt of our power be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. And fyrſt that worldly care<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / &amp; fleſhly cogitacions / ſuche as drawe vs from contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placion of God be expellid from them / that it may frely without interrupcion call vppon God.<note place="margin">Note.</note> But howe diffyſed &amp; harde is this one thing in prayer to performe / knoweth no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better / then ſuch as in their prayers / not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to remayne within the bandes of their owne vanitie / but as it were rauiſhed / do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to a pure worde of God / aſking not ſuch thinges as the blinde &amp; foliſh reaſon of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth / but what may be pleſaunt &amp; acceptable in Gods preſens.<note place="margin">Petre. 5</note> Our aduerſary ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / at all tymes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſing vs about / is neuer more buſy then when we adreſſe &amp; be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vs to prayer / for
<pb n="iij" facs="tcp:8582:31"/>
o / how ſecretly &amp; ſubtilly crepeth he in oure breſtes / &amp; calling vs backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God / cauſeth vs to forget what we haue to do.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Let euer man iudge his owne hart.</head>
                     <p>SO that frequently / when we with all reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rince ſhould ſpeake to God / we fynde oure harts talki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with the vanites of the world or with the foliſh imaginacions of our own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent / ſo that without the ſprete of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶How the ſprete maketh interceſſion for vs.<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>SVportinge oure infirmities / mightely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king interceſſion for vs / with inceſſable gro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / which can not be expreſſed with tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / hope is there none / that any thing we can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire / according to Gods wil. I meane not that the holy ghoſt mournes or prayes / but that he ſterith vp our myndes / geuing vnto vs a deſire or boldnes for to pray / &amp; cauſeth vs to mourne when we are extracted &amp; plucked there from / which thinges to conceiue / no ſtrength of man ſuffiſeth / neither is able of it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Who prayeth not.</note> Hereof it is playne / that ſuch as vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de not what they praye / or expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des not / or declare not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of their hartes / clearly in Gods preſens. And in tyme of praier / to their poſſibilite with out their expell vaine cogitacions from their myndes profyt / nothinge in prayer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Why we ſhould pray / and alſo vnderſtande what we do praye.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                        </label> BVt ſome wil obiect &amp; ſay: albeit / we vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not what we do pray / ye God vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth / who knoweth the ſecret of our hartes / knoweth alſo what we nede / 
<pb facs="tcp:8582:32"/>
although we expounde not or declare our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſites vnto hym. Such me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verely declareth them ſelfs / neuer to haue vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding / what profit prayer ment / nor too what ende Ieſus Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs to pray. Which is firſt that our hartes may be enflamed with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall feare / honor &amp; loue of God / to whome we runne for ſupporte &amp; helpe / when ſoeuer daunger or neceſſitie requireth / that we ſo ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge to notefye oure deſiers in his preſence / may teache vs what is earneſtly to be axed / &amp; what not. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darely that we knowing our peticions to be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by God / to hym alone we muſte referre &amp; geue lande and prayſe. And that we euer hauing his infinite goodnes / fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>id in our myndes / may conſtantly abide to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that / which with feruent prayers we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier / <note place="margin">Vvhif God deffereth to graunt our praier</note> for ſometime God deffereth or prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to graunt oure peticions / for the excerciſion &amp; trial of our faythe / &amp; not that he ſlepeth / or is abſente frome vs at any tyme / but that with more gladnes we mighte receiue that / whiche with longe expectacion we haue abyden / that therby we aſſured of his eternall prouidence / (ſo farre as the infirmetie of our corruptie &amp; moſt weked nature wil permitte) doubte not / but his merciful hande ſhal releaf vs in moſte vrgent neceſſite &amp; extreme tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch men as teacheth vs / that neceſſarely it is not required that we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not what we pray / becauſe God knoweth what we nede wold alſo teach vs / that neither we honor God nor yet referre / or geue vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites
<pb n="iiij" facs="tcp:8582:32"/>
receiued / for howe ſhall we honor and prayſe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whoſe goodnes &amp; liberalite we know not / how ſhal we know / oneles we receiue / and ſometime haue experiens. And howe ſhall we know that we haue receiued / onleſſe we know verely what we haue aſked.</p>
                     <p>The ſeconde thinge to be obſerued in perfit prayer is / that ſtanding in the preſens of God / we be found ſuch as beryes to his holy law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence / <note place="margin">Prou. 18.</note> earneſtly repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting our iniquite paſſed and inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to leade a new lyfe / for otherwiſe in vayne are all our prayers / as it is written / who withdrawes his ear / that he wil not hear the lawe of God / his oration or prayer ſhalbe abhominable. And alſo ye ſhall multeply your prayers / &amp; I ſhal not heare / becauſe your han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are full of bloude / that is off all crueltie and miſcheuous workes. And the ſprete of God appeareth by the mouthe of the blynde / <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> whome Ieſus Chriſt doth illuminate by theſe wordes / we knowe that God heareth no ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners / that is ſuch as glories / &amp; do continew in iniquites.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinners are not hard of God</head>
                     <p>SO that of neceſſite true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be had / &amp; paſſe before perfitte prayer / or ſyncere inuocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gods name. And vnto theſe two preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces muſt be annexed the thride which is the directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſelfs in godes pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence. Vtterly refuſing &amp; caſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of own iuſtice with all cogitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; opinion therof / that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge proceding of our ſelfes / that we ſhould be harde / for all ſuche as auaunce / boaſt or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende any thing vpon their own iuſtice / from
<pb facs="tcp:8582:33"/>
the preſence of his mercye / repellith &amp; holdeth with the hygh proude phareſey. And therfore the moſte holy men / we fynde in praiers moſt deiected &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble.<note place="margin">Pſal. 79.</note> Dauid ſayeth: o Lorde our ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour help vs / for the glory of thy own name deliuer vs / be mercifull vnto oure ſynnes for thy owne name. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber not oure olde ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities / but haſt thou o Lorde / &amp; let thy mercy preuent vs. Ieremie ſayeth: yf oure iniquities beare teſtimoni againſt vs / do thou accordyng to thy owne name. And behold I ſay / thou art crabbid / O Lorde / becauſe we haue ſynned / &amp; are repleniſhed with all wickednes.<note place="margin">Eſay. 64</note> And oure iuſtice is like a filthy clothe. &amp;c. But now O Lord / thou art our father / we are claye / thou arte the worke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; we the workema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip of thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.<note place="margin">Daniel. 9</note> Be not crabid O Lord / remember not our iniquities for euer. And Daniel great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did of God / maketh in his prayer moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe wordes / we be ſinners / &amp; haue offeded / we haue done vngodly / &amp; falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / but not in our own righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes make we our prayers before the / but thy moſt rych &amp; great mercy bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g we forth for vs. O Lord heare / Lord be merciful / &amp; ſpare vs Lord / atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / helpe &amp; ceaſe not my God / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thy names ſake / do it for thy people &amp; thy citie called after thy name. Behold / that in theſe prayers is no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their own iuſtice / their owne ſatiſfaction / or their owne merites / but moſt humble confeſſion / procedinge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull and penitent harte / hauing nothinge wherupon it might depende / but the mercy of
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:8582:33"/>
God alone / who had promiſed to be their God that is their help / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort / defendor / &amp; deliuerer (as he hath alſo don to vs by Ieſus Criſt) in ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of tribulacion.<note place="margin">Note.</note> And therfore / they / diſpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid not / but after knowlege of ther Sinnes / callid for mercy &amp; obtayned theſame / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is playne / that ſuche men as in theyr prayrs / haue reſpecte to any vertue / proceding of them ſelffe / thinkinge therby theyr prayrs to be accepted / neuer prayd aright.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶What faſtinge almoſes dedes are without praye.</head>
                     <p>ANd albeit to feruent prayer be Ioynyd / faſtinge / waking and almoſ dede / yet are none of theſe the cauſe / that God dothe except our prayrs but they are ſpurres which ſuffer vs not to vary / but make vs more able to continew in prayr / <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.86.</note> which the mercy of God dothe accepte. But here maye it be obiectid / Dauid praythe / kepe mi lyfe o Lorde for I am holy / o Lorde here my iuſtice and ſuffer me not to be confoundid / <note place="margin">4. reg. 20</note> and Ezechius reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de I beſeche the / that I haue walked righteou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſly before the / and that I haue wrought that which is good in thy ſight. Theſe wordes are not ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glorious / neither yet truſting in ther owne workes.<note place="margin">Note we</note> But here in they te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtefy them ſelfes to be the ſonnes of God by regeneracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to whom he promiſid alwayes to be merciful / &amp; at al tims to hear theyr praiers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶The cauſe of ther boldnes was Ieſus Criſt.</head>
                     <p>ANd ſo theyr wordes ſpringe a wontyd / conſtante and feruent faythe / ſurely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuinge
<pb facs="tcp:8582:34"/>
that as God of hys infinitie mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy / had callid them to his knowlege / not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe them to walke after theyr owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wickednes / but partly had through them to confirme them to his holy lawe / and that for the promiſed ſedes ſake / ſo mighte he not leaue them deſtitute or comfort / conſolacion and defence / in ſo great and extreme neceſſite. And ſo theyr iuſtice a leage they not to glory therof / or to put truſt therin / but to confyrme and ſtrengthen them ſelfes in Godes promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / and this conſolation I wolde wyſhe to al Chriſtians in theyr prayers / a teſtimony of good conſcience to aſſure them of Godes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes / but to obtayne what they aſke muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende vpon his mercy / al opinion and through of our own iuſtice layd aſide. And more ouer Dauid in the wordes aboue compareth hym ſelfe with Kinge Saule / and with the reſt of his enemies / who wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gfully did perſecute hym / deſyiringe of God that they preuayle not agaynſte hym (as who ſaye) iniuſtlye doo they perſecute me &amp; therfore according to my innocenſi defende me / for otherwyſe he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſith him ſelf mooſt greuouſly to haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did God / as in the precident places he clearly teſtifieth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Ipocriſie is not alowid with god.</head>
                     <p>THirdly in prayer is to obſerued / that what we aſke of God / that we moſte erniſtly deſier / the ſame knowleginge vs to be indigent voyde therof / and that God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone may graunte the peticion of our hartes.<note place="margin">mark wel</note> For nothyng is more odious before God then
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:8582:34"/>
Ipocriſie and diſſimulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (that is) whan ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe aſke of God a thinge / wherof he hathe no neade / or that he beleueth to attayne / by others then by God allone. As if a man aſke of God remiſſion of his ſinnes / thinkinge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe to obtayne theſame by his owne workes / papiſtical pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / merytes of maſſes / or whatſoeuer other meanes / dothe mocke God / and in ſuche cauſes doth a greate num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber offende principally / the mighte and riche of the earth / who for a common confuetude &amp; cuſtome / wil pray this parte of Godes prayer geue vs this day our dayly breade / <note place="margin">Dayly bread.</note> that is a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derate and reſonable ſuſtentacion / &amp; yet theyr owne hartes will teſtefy that they neade not ſo to pray / ſeinge they abounde in al wordly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace and felicitie. I meane not that riche men ſhould not pray this parte of prayer / but I wolde they vnderſtode / what they ougt to pray in it (wherof we intende after to ſpeake) and that they aſked nothinge wherof they felt not them ſelfs maruelous ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gent and nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, / for oneleſſe we cal in verite / he wil not graunte / &amp; without we ſpeake with oure hole harte / we ſhall not finde him. The fourthe rule / neceſſary to be folowed in prayer / is a ſure hope to obtayn what we aſke for nothing more offendeth God / then when we aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e doubtyng wether he wil graunte oure pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticions / for in ſo doinge we doubt if G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d be true / if he be mighty and good.<note place="margin">Iaco. 1.</note> Suche faythe Iames obtayne nothynge of God / and therfore Iheſus Chriſte commaundeth
<pb facs="tcp:8582:35"/>
that we fyrmly beleue to obtayne whatſoeuer we aſke / for al thinges is poſſible vnto hym that beleueth / and therfore in our prayrs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes is to be expellid deſperacion.<note place="margin">Note wel</note> I meane not that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in extreamite of troble / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be without a preſent dolour / and without a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter feare of troble to folow.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Sporris ſtire vs to prayer</note>Troble &amp; feare are the very ſpures to pray for when man compaſſid aboute with vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment calamyte / and vexid with continual ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citude / hauinge by healpe of man / no hope of deliueraunce with ſore oppreſſed an puniſhed harte / ferynge alſo greater puniſhement to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low frome the depe pyt of trybulacion / dothe cal to God / for comforte and ſupporte.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶God deliuerith his choſen frome theyr eny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes.</head>
                     <p>THat prayer aſcendith into goddes preſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and retourneth not in vayne / as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid in the vehement perſecucion of Sau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le / <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.</note> hunted and chaſed from euery hole / fearing that one day or other he ſhulde fal in to the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of his perſecutors / after that he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned / that no place of reſt was lefte for him vehemently / prayde ſayinge / o Lorde which art my God / in whome I haue truſted / ſaue me frome al that perſecute me / and delyuer me / let not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s man (meninge Kinge Saule) deuoure my life as the lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth his pray / ſeing their is no man to delyuer me / in the myddeſt of theſe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guiſhes / the goodnes of God ſuſtainid hym / that the preſent tribulacion was tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable / and the infallible promyſis of God / ſo
<pb n="vij" facs="tcp:8582:35"/>
aſſured him of deliueraunce / that feare was partly nitegate and gone / as playnly apereth to ſuche as diligently marke the proſſes of his prayer / for after longe meniſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nge and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teninge made to his enemye / he concludith with theſe wordes. The dollor which he ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith vnto me / ſhal fal vppon his own head / &amp; the violence wherwith he wolde haue oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me / ſhal caſt doun his owne head / and I ſhal magnify the Lord / accordinge to his iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / and ſhal prayſe the name of the moſt higeſt.<note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte to the wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / being in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is not written for Dauid only / but for al ſuche as ſhal ſuffer tribulacion / to the ende of the worlde / for I the writer hereof (let this be ſayd to the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; prayſe of God alon) in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhe of mynde / &amp; veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; afflic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion called vnto the Lorde / when not only the vngodly / but euen my faytheful brother / yea and my owne ſelfe / that is / al natural vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge. Iudge my cauſe to be irremydiceble &amp; yet in my greateſt calamyte. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes wher moſt cruel / wold his eternal wiſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / that my hande ſhuld write (farre contrary to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of carnal reaſon) which his mercy hathe prouyd true / and therfore dare I be in the veryte of Godes worde to permit that not withſtandinge / the vehemency of tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / the longe continuance therof / the deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of al men / the fearfulnes dolore / and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhe of our own hartes / yet yf we cal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to God / that by expectacion of al men he ſhal delyuer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8582:36"/>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Notewel</hi> Vvhere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant praier is, this grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the peti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion. Pſal. 41. Pſal. 119.</note>Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke him ſelfe vnworthy to cal and pray vnto God / becauſe he hath greuouſly offendid God in tymes paſt / but let hym bryng to God a ſorowful and repentynge harte / ſayinge with Dauid / heale my ſoule o Lorde / for I haue offendid agaynſt the / before I fel in myſery I tranſgreſſed / but now let me obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thy commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes.</p>
                     <p>To mitegate or eaſe the ſorowes of our wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>did conſcience / two playſters hath our moſt prudent phiſition prouyd to geue vs / in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for to pray / notwithſtanding the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of offences committed / that is a precepte and a promyſe / the precept or commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement to pray is vniuerſal frequently inculeate and repetyd in Godes ſcripturs.<note place="margin">Mat. 7. Pſal. 49. Matt. 26. 1. Tim. 2. 1. Teſſa. 5</note> Aſke and it ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be geuen vnto you. Cal vppon me in the day of thy tribulacion / watche and pray that ye fal not into temptacion. I commaunde that euer ye make deprecacions / pray inceſſable and geue thankes in al thynge / which commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement / who contemneth or diſpiſeth / doth e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ally ſinne with hym that doth ſteale.</p>
                     <p>For as this commaundement / thou ſhal not ſteale / is a precept negatyue / ſo thou ſhalt pray is commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement affirmatyne / and God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth equal obedience of / and to al his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes (yet more boldly wil I ſay) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neceſſite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraynth deſireth / <note place="margin">Notewel</note> not ſupporte and helpe at God / doth prouoke his wrathe no leſſe then ſuche as make falſſe Gods / doo or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly deny God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Who prayth not in tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denieth God.</head>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="vij" facs="tcp:8582:36"/>FOr like as it is to know no phiſicion or medicine / and in knowinge them refuſe to vſe and receyue the ſame / ſo not to cal vppon God in thy tribulacion is / lyke as thou not God / or els vtterly denye hym.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Not to pray is ſinne moſt odious.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> Why ceaſſe we to cal inſtantly to his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy / hauinge his commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement ſo to do aboue al our iniquities / we worke mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt contemtion and diſpiſinge / when by we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kid negligens / we delay to cal for his ſupporte / we doth cal to God obeyth his wil / <note place="margin">Iere. 7.</note> &amp; fyndeth therin no ſmall conſolacion / knowynge no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfice / ſo acceptable to his maieſtye / as hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedience is.</p>
                     <p>To his commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement he addeth his moſt vndoubted promyſe in many places / <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> aſke and ye ſhal haue / ſeke and ye ſhal fynde / <note place="margin">Ierem. 27</note> and by the Prophet Ieremy ye ſhal cal vppon me / and I ſhal hear you / ye ſhal ſeke and ſhal find me / and by Eſaye / may the father forget his natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral ſonne / or the mother the child of her wom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be / and although they do / yet ſhal I not forget ſuche as cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. And hereto correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and agree the wordes of Ieſus Chriſt / ſaying / yf ye beynge wekid / <note place="margin">Lucke. 1.</note> can geue good gyftes to your ſonnes / muche more my celeſtial father ſhal geue the holy ghoſte too them that aſke of hym. And that we ſhould not thinke God to be abſent or not heare vs accurreth. Moyſes ſaying / <note place="margin">Deut. 4</note> there is no nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue theyr godes ſo adherent or nyghe vnto them as our God is preſent / at al our prayers. And the pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt
<pb facs="tcp:8582:37"/>
/ nyghe is the lord to al / which cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in veryte / &amp; Ieſus Criſt ſayth / whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer are two or thre gathered together in my name / there am I in the myddes of them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Reddines of God to heare ſinners.</head>
                     <p>THat we ſhal not thynke that God wil not heare vs / Eſay ſayng befor they crye I ſhal hear / and while they yet ſpeake / I ſhal aunſwer / and alſo yf at euen / come ſorowe or calamiti / before the morninge ſpringe I ſhal redreſſe &amp; turne gladnes / and his moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table worde / ſpoken not to carnal Iſrael only / but to al men ſore oppreſſed / abidinge Gods deliuerance. Frome a moment and a lyttel ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon haue I turned my face frome the / but in euerlaſtinge mercye ſhall I comforte the.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶The hope to obteyn our peticions / ſhuld de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pende vppon the promyſes of God.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> Stony are the harts / whome ſo many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde moſt ſwete &amp; ſure promiſ is dothe not molyfye / wherevppon ſhoulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend the hope to obtayne our peticions / the dingnite or vnworthynes of our ſelfes is not to be regarded / for albeit to the choſen / which are departed in holynes and purite of lyfe / we be inferiors / yet in that parte we are equal in that we haue / the ſame Commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement to pray / and the ſame promiſe to be harde / for he eſtimeth not the prayer / neither grauntith the peticion / for any dingnite of the perſon that prayth / but for his owne promyſe ſake. And therfore ſayth Dauid.<note place="margin">1. King. 7</note> Thou haſt promyſed vnto thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / o Lorde that thou wilte build
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:8582:37"/>
an houſe for hym / and therefore thy ſeruaunt hath founde conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t matter to pray in thy preſence. Now ſo o Lord God / thou art God / and thy wonders are true / thou haſte ſpoken theſe good thinges vnto thy ſeruaunte / begin therfore to do / according to thy promiſe / mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie o Lorde the houſholde of thy ſeruaunte.<note place="margin">Gene. 23.</note> Beholde / Dauid altogether dependith vppon Gods promiſe / as alſo did Iacobe / who after he had confeſſed hym ſelfe vnworthy of all the benefites receyued / yet dare he boldely aſke greater benefytes in tymes ſubſequent / &amp; that becauſe God had promiſed. In the lyke maner let vs be encouraged / too aſke whatſoeuer the goodnes of God hath frely promiſed / what we ſhould aſke pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipally we after ſhal heare.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Obſeruacion in godly prayer.</head>
                     <p>THe fifth obſeruacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which godly praier requireth / is the perfyt knowledge off the aduocate interceffour &amp; mediatour for ſeing no man is of hym ſelfe worthy to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare / or apeare in Gods preſence by reaſon / that in all men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually reſteth ſynne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Of neceſſyte we muſt haue a mediator.</head>
                     <p>WHiche by the ſelfe doth offende the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of God / reaſinge alſo / debate / ſtryfe / hatered / and deuiſion betwixt his inuio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lable iuſtice and vs. Wherunto / oneles ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be made by any other then by our ſelfs / ſo littel hope reſteth that any thyng from him. We can attayne / that no ſuerty may we haue with hym at all.</p>
                     <p>To examine vs of hys horrible confuſion / 
<pb facs="tcp:8582:38"/>
knowinge that our mindes moſt fragile / here by continually ſhuld haue ben deiectid / our merciful father hathe geuen vnto vs his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotton ſonne Ieſus Chriſt to be aduoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and foreſpeaker for vs / <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. Hebre. 8.</note> that we ledde by ſuche a guyde with whoſe iuſtice (yf in him we beleue) we are ſo clede that we may with bold<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>payr and apeare before the trone of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des mercy / doubtyng nothing / but whatſoeuer we aſke by our mediator / <note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> the ſame we ſhal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn in moſe opportunite.</p>
                     <p>Here is moſt diligently to be eſchewed / that without our mediatour for ſpeaker / &amp; peace ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker / <note place="margin">Note dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, by Vvhom vve muſt praie.</note> we enter into prayer / ſo the benifite of ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as pray without Ieſus Criſt / are not only vayn / but alſo they are odious / &amp; abhomenable before God / which thing to vs in the leuitical prieſthode mooſt euident was prefigurate &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarid / for as within ſantum ſantoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entred no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. par. 26.</note> but the hige prieſt allone / and as al ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces offred by any other then by prieſtes only / prouoked the wraught of God vppon the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice maker / ſo who dothe intende to enter into goddes preſence / or to make prayrs without Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Criſt ſhal find nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / but fearful iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; horrible da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacion. Wherfore it is playne that Turkes &amp; Iewes not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that they do appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly / <note place="margin">Turkes Iewes.</note> &amp; moſt verfently pray vnto God / who created heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth / who guideth &amp; ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth theſame / who defendeth the good / &amp; puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the euil / yet neuer are theyr prayers plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant vnto God / neither honor they his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty in any thyng / becauſe they acknowlege not
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:8582:38"/>
Iheſus Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶When we be not hearde.</head>
                     <p>FOr who honoreth not the ſonne / honorith not the father / for as the lawe is a ſtatute / that we ſhall call vnto God / and as the promiſe is made that he ſhal heare vs / ſo are we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded only to cal by Ieſus Chriſt / <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> by whome alone our peticions we obtayne / for in hym allone are al the promiſes of God confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleant / wherof without all contreuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes / it is playne that ſuche as haue caullid or calleth preſentlye vnto God / by anye other meane / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Ieſus Criſt allone / doth nothing regarde Godes wil / but obſtinatly preuaricat / &amp; do agaynſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes / &amp; therfore neither obtai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei their peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / nor yet haue en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tres in his mercy. For no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther (ſayith Ieſus Chriſt / but by me he is the right way / who declineth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him errith and goyth wronge / he is oure leder / whome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out we folowe / we ſhal walke in darknes / &amp; he alone is our captain / without whome neither praiſe nor victory we ſhal obtayne agaynſt ſuch as depend vpon the interceſſion of ſayntes / no otherwyſe wil I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend / but ſhortly touche the propertis of a perfyt mediatour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Interceſſion to ſayntes.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt are the wordes moſt ſure of Paule / a mediatoure is not the mediatour of one / that is / whereſoeuer is required a mediator / there are alſo two parties / to wyte one party offendant &amp; the other party / which is offendid whiche partiſe by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe maye in no wiſe be reconſiled.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8582:39"/>Secondly the mediator / <note place="margin">Mediator.</note> which taketh vppon hym the reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiling of theſe two parties / muſt be ſuche one as haue truſte and fauor of both parties in ſome thinges / And differre frome bothe / and muſte be cleane and innocent / alſo of the cryme / committed agaynſt the party of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended / let thys be more playne by thys ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent declaration.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Aungels may not be mediators.</head>
                     <p>THe eternall God ſtandeth vppon the one parte / and all naturall men / deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Adam vpon the other / the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite iuſtice of God is ſo offended with the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſſion of all men / that in no wyſe can amyte be made / excepte ſuche one be founde as fully maye make ſatiſfaccion / for mans offences / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the ſonnes of men none was founde able. For all they were founde criminall in the faulte of one / and God infinite in iuſtice muſt abhorre the ſocietie and ſacrifice of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. And vnto aungelles / what preuailed the preuarication of man / who albeit / they wolde haue interponed them ſelfes mediators / had not the iuſtice infinite / who ſhall here be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d peace maker. The infinite goodnes and mercy of God / might not ſuffer the perpetuall loſſe and repudiacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his creature / &amp; therfore his eternall wyſedome / prouyde ſuch an medya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hauing wherwith to ſatiſfy. The iuſtice of God differeth alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the godhead / his onely ſonne / cledde in the nature of manhead / who interponed him ſelf mediator / not as ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Ieſus Chriſt / God &amp; man is mediator.</head>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:8582:39"/>FOr the pure humanitie of Chriſte of it ſelfe / might neither make interceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor ſatiſfaccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs / but God &amp; man in that that he is God / he might complete the will of the father / &amp; in that / that he is man pure and cleane / without ſpot or ſinne he might offer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice / for purgacion of our ſynnes &amp; ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods iuſtice / without ſainctes. Haue theſe twoo godhead equale with the father / &amp; humanite without ſynne / the office of media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors they may not vſurpe / <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                        </label> but here wilbe obiec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted / who knoweth not Ieſus Chriſt /  to be the onely mediator of our redemcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Aūſwere. </seg>
                        </label> but that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedites or letteth nothing. Sainctes and holy men / to be mediators to make interceſſion for vs /  as though that Ieſus Chriſte had bene one houre or mediator / &amp; after had reſined thoffice vnto his ſeruauntes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Who maketh other mediators then Ieſus Chriſt / taketh ouer from hym.</head>
                     <p>DO not ſuch men ientelly intreate Ieſus Chriſt / detracting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſuch porcion of his honor / otherwiſe ſpeaketh the ſcriptures of God / teſtefying hym to be made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; to haue proued oure infirmites to haue ſuffred death willingly / to haue ouercome the ſame / &amp; all to this ende / that he might be oure perpetuall hyghe ſouerayne &amp; pryſe / <note place="margin">Heb. 6.7.9.10.</note> in whoſe place or dignitie none other mighte entre / as Ihon ſayth / yf any man ſinne / we haue an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate with the father / euen Ieſus Chriſt the iuſt / marke well this wordes / Ihon ſayth / <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. Rom. 8.</note> we haue preſently a ſufficiente aduocate / whome
<pb facs="tcp:8582:40"/>
Paule affirmeth to ſit / at the righte hande of God the father / and to be the only mediator betwene God and man / for he alone (ſayeth Ambroſe) is our mouth / by whome we ſpeake to God / he is our eyes / by whome we ſe God / &amp; alſo oure righte hande / by whome we offer any thinge vnto the father / who oneleſſe he make interceſſion / neither we / neither any off the ſainctes maye haue any ſociete or felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God.<note place="margin">Libro de Iſaac de anima. True mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres.</note>
                        <note place="margin">Note di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently.</note> What creator may ſay to God the father / let mankinde be receyued into thy fauoure / for the payne of hys tranſgreſſion that haue I ſuſtayned in my owne bodye / for hys cauſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed with all infirmety became I the moſt contempted &amp; diſprayſed of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and yet in my mouth was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no diſceyt nor gyle / but always obedient to thy will / ſuffred death / that for mankynd.<note place="margin">Obedience of Chriſt.</note> And therfore behold not the ſinner / but me / who by my infinitie iuſtice / haue perfetly ſatiſfied for hys offences / maye any other Ieſus Chriſt / except I / in theſe wordes make interceſſion for ſinners / yf they may not then / are they not neither mediators nor interceſſors.<note place="margin">Libro co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me niz, ca</note> For albeit / ſayeth Auguſtine Chriſtians do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend one another vnto God in theyr prayers / yet not make interciſſion / or dare vſurpeth office of a mediator / not Paule albeit vnder the head / he was a principale me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre / yet becauſe he commendeth hym ſelfe too the prayer of faithfull men <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                        </label> yf any do obiecte. Such is not the condicions of the ſaynctes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted /  who nowe hathe put of immortalite / and beareth no lenger the fragilite of the fleſh.
<pb n="xij" facs="tcp:8582:40"/>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Aūſwer. </seg>
                        </label> Which albeit / I graunte to be moſte true /  yet are they all compelled to caſte theyr crounes before hym that dothe ſitte in the throne / <note place="margin">Apoc. 6.</note> knowleginge them ſelfes to be deliuered from greate affliccion / too haue bene purged by the bloud of the Lam / and therfore none of them do attempt to be a mediator / ſeynge they ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue being / nor iuſtice of them ſelfe / but in ſo great light of the Goſpel (prayſe be to the omnipotent) it is not neceſſary vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter longe to remayne.<note place="margin">Note this wel.</note> Some ſay / we will vſe but one mediator Ieſus Chriſt to God the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / but we muſte haue ſainctes / and chiefly the virgin Mary / mother of Ieſus Chriſt too praye for vs vnto hym.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Agaynſte ſuche as wolde haue mediators too Ieſus Chriſte.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Lace / whoſoeuer is ſo mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / ſheweth playnly them ſelf to know nothing of Ieſus Chriſt righteouſly / is he who diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen / conuerſed among ſinners. Commaunded all / vexid ſore / <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> ſeke too come vnto hym / who hanginge vppon the croſſe / prayde fyrſt for hys enemies / become newe ſo vntractable / that he will not heare vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute a parſon to be a meane. O Lorde / open the eye of ſuche / that they maye clearly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue thy infinete kyndnes / gentelnes and loue towardes mankynde. Aboue all precidentes is to be obſerued / that what we aſke of God / oughte too de proffitable to oure ſelfe and too others / and hurte or daunger of no man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8582:41"/>Secondarely / we muſte conſider whether our peticions extenditeth to ſpirituall or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall thinges.<note place="margin">Spirituall thinges ſhoulde be axid vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Spirituall thinges / ſuch as are deliuerance from impiete / remiſſion of their ſinnes / the gifte of the holy ghoſte / and of lyfe euerlaſting ſhould we deſire abſolutely / with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any condicion by Ieſus Chriſt / in whome alone all theſe are promiſed / &amp; in aſking here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of / we ſhould not pray thus: O father forgeue our ſinnes / yf thou wilt / for his will he hath expreſſed / ſayinge: as I lyue / I deſire not the death of a ſynner / but rather that he conuert and lyue / <note place="margin">mark wel</note> which in mutable and ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned othe / who calleth in doubt / maketh God a liar / and ſo farre as in hym lyeth / wolde ſpoyle God of hys godhead / for he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be God / but he muſt be eternal &amp; infallible veritie / as Ihon ſayth:<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.</note> This is the teſtimony / which God hath teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of hys ſonne / that who beleueth in the ſonne / hath eternal lyfe to the verite whereof we ſhoulde ſtedfaſtly cleue / although calamite and worldly dolor apprehendith vs / <note place="margin">2. Reg. 15</note> as Dauid exiled from hys kyngdom / and depriued of all hys glorie / ſecluded not frome God / but ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly beleued reconſiliacion by the promyſe made / notwithſtandinge that all creators in earth had refuſed / obiected / &amp; rebelled agaynſt hym / happy is the man whome thou ſhalle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire o Lorde.<note place="margin">Corporal thinges.</note> In aſking corporal thinges / firſt let vs inquire / yf we be at peace with God in our conſcience by Ieſus Chriſte / Fyrmly bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge our ſinnes to be remitted in hys bloud. Secondly / let vs inquire our owne hartes / yf
<pb n="xiij" facs="tcp:8582:41"/>
we know temporall ryches or ſubſtaunce / not to come to man by accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te fortune or chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / neither yet by the induſtre &amp; diligence of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s labor / but to be the liberall gyft of God onely / wherof we ought to lande &amp; prayſe hys good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / wyſedome / &amp; prouidence alone.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶What ſhould be prayed for.</head>
                     <p>ANd yf this we do truly knowlege &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe / let vs boldely aſke of him / whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is neceſſary for vs / as ſuſtentacion of the body / health therof / defence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſery deliueraunce from troble / tranquilite &amp; peace to our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthes / proſperous ſucceſſe in our vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / labours &amp; affaires / &amp; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer which God wil / we aſke all of hym too certify vs / that all thing ſtande in his regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and diſpocition. And alſo by aſking and recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge this corporall commodites / we may taſt of hys ſweatnes / and be inflamed with hys loue / that therby our fayth of reconciliation &amp; remiſſion of our ſynnes maye be exerciſed and take increace.</p>
                     <p>But in aſayng ſuche temporal thinges / we muſt obſerue.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note we</hi> Vvhy Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> differreth or prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unt vs our peticion.</note> Fyrſt / that yf God differrith or prolonge to graunt our peticions / euen ſo long that he doth apparantly reiecte vs / yet let vs not ſeace to call / preſcribing to hym / neither tyme nor maner of deliuerance / as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten / yf he prolonge tyme abyde paciently vpon hym / and alſo let not the faythful be to haſty. For God ſometyme differreth / and will not haſtely graunt to the probacion of oure eonti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / as the wordes of Iſeus Chriſt teſtefie / 
<pb facs="tcp:8582:42"/>
&amp; alſo that we may receiue with greater glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / which with hardent deſire we long haue loked for / as Anna / Sara &amp; Elizabeth / after great ingnontye of their barranenes &amp; ſterilite / receiued frute of their boſumes with ioye.</p>
                     <p>Secondarely / becauſe we knowe the churche at all tymes to be vnder the croſſe / in aſkynge temporall commodites / and ſpecially deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce frome troble let vs offer vnto God obedience / <note place="margin">2. Re. 15.</note> yf it ſhall pleaſe hys goodnes we lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger be exerciſed / that we may paciently abyde it / as Dauid deſired to be reſtored to his kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome / what tyme he was exiled by his owne ſonne offereth vnto God obedience / ſaying: yf I haue founde fauoure in the preſence of the Lorde / he ſhall bryng me home agayne / and yf he ſhall ſaye / thou pleaſeſt my not longer too beare auctorite / I am obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / let hym do what ſemed good vnto hym.<note place="margin">Dani. 3.</note> And the thre chyldren vnto Nabuchodonoſor ſaye: we knowe that our God / whome we worſhip / maye deliuer vs / but if it ſhall not pleaſe hym ſo to do / let it be knowen to the o kynge / that thy Gods we will not worſhip.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Better it is to obey God then man.</head>
                     <p>HEre geue they a true confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their perfit fayth / knowing nothinge to be impoſſible to the omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of God / affirming alſo themſelf to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in his mercy for otherwiſe the nature of man coulde not willingly geue it ſelf to ſo horrible a torment / but offer they vnto God moſte humble obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to be deliuered at hys pleaſure &amp; godly
<pb n="xiiij" facs="tcp:8582:42"/>
will. As we ſhoulde do in all afflictions / for we knowe not what too aſke / or deſire as we ought / that is the frayle fleſh / oppreſſeth with feare and payne / deſireth deliueraunce euer abhorring and drawing backe from obedience geuen. (O Chriſten brother / I write by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience) but the ſprite of God calleth backe the mynde to obedience / that albeit / it doth deſire and abyde for deliueraunce / yea / wolde it not repyng the goodwil of God inceſſantly aſketh that it may abyde with pacience. Howe harde is the battail / no man knoweth but he / whiche in hym ſelfe hath ſuffred triall / <note place="margin">Note wel</note> it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that God ſometime doth graunt the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the ſprete / wyle he yet defferreth the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſired of the fleſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶The peticion of the ſprete.<note place="margin">Gene. 9</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS who doubteth / but God did mitigate the heauines of Ioſeph / althoughe he ſent not haſty deliueraunce in his longe impriſoneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; that as he gaue hym fauour / in the ſighte of his iaylour / ſo inwardly alſo gaue he vnto hym conſolation in ſprite. And more ouer / God ſometime grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſprite / where all vtterly he repelleth the deſyre of the fleſh / for the peticion always of the ſprete is / that we may obtayn to felicite wherunto we nedes muſt enter by tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and the finall death / both which doth euer the nature of man abhorre / and therfore the fleſhe vnder the croſſe / &amp; at the ſight of death / call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h and truſteth for haſty deliueraunce / but God who alone knoweth what is expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Fleſh ſtriueth agaynſte the ſprete.</head>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8582:43"/>
                        <note place="margin">Percecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ful.</note>Sometyme prolongeth the deliuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of hys choſen / and ſometime permitteth them to drinke / before the maturite of age / the bitter cuppe of corporal death / that therby they may receyue medicine and care from all infirmite / but who doubtith / but Ihon the Baptiſer / de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to haue ſene more dayes of Ieſus Chriſt / and to haue bene longer with hym in conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſacion.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 7.</note> Or that Steuen wolde not haue labo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red more dayes in preaching Chriſtes goſpell / whome neuertheleſſe / both he ſuffered haſtely to vnderlye the ſtatute and generall ſentence. And albeit / we ſe therfore no apparant / helpe to oure ſelfe / nor yet to others afflicted / let vs not ceaſe to call / thinkinge oure prayers to be in vayne / whatſoeuer become of oure bodies.<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte to the afflictyd</note> God ſhall geue vnſpeakable comforte too the ſprete / and ſhall turne all to our commodite / by our owne expectacion. The cauſe I am ſo longe and tedious in this matter is / I knowe how harde the battaill is betwixt the fleſhe &amp; the ſprete.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Impedimentes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mith of the weakenes off the fleſhe.</head>
                     <p>SPrete vnder the heauy croce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of affliccion / where no worldely defence / but preſence death doth appeare / I know the grudging and murmoringe complayntes of the fleſhe / I know the anger wrathe &amp; indignacion / which it conceiueth agaynſt God / calling all hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes into doubte / &amp; beinge redy euery houre / vtterly to fall from hym. Agaynſt whiche all reſteth in faith / prouoking vs to call inſtantly
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:8582:43"/>
and to praye for aſſiſtaunce of Gods ſprete. Whereunto / yf we continew our moſte deſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rat calamites / ſhall he turne to gladnes &amp; ioye and proſperous fyne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶To the o Lorde alone be prayſe / for with experience I write this &amp; ſpeake: it is not too be permitted / where / for whome / and at what tyme we ought to praye.</head>
                     <p>PRiuate prayer / <note place="margin">Priuate prayer. Matt. 6.</note> ſuch as men ſecretly offer vnto God by them ſelfe / require no ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall place / althoughe that Ieſus Chriſte commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth / when we praye to enter in our chaumber / and to cloſe the dore after vs / &amp; ſo to pray ſecretly vnto oure father / <note place="margin">To enter in to thi cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber to pray</note> whereby he wolde we ſhoulde chuſe to our prayers ſuche place as might offer leaſt occaſion too call vs backe from prayer / and alſo that we ſhoulde expell forthe of our myndes in tyme of oure prayer all vayne cogitacions / for otherwyſe Ieſus Chriſt hym ſelfe doth obſerue no ſpecial place of prayers / for we finde hym ſometyme pray in mounte Oliuete / ſometyme in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerte / ſometime in the temple.<note place="margin">Actu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 10.</note> Peter coueteth to praye vppon the toppe of the houſe / Paule prayeth in pryſon / &amp; was harde of God / who alſo commaundeth men to pray in all places / <note place="margin">Priuate pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to praie in.</note> lifting vp vnto God pure and cleane handes / as we fynde that the Prophetes &amp; muſte holy men did / whereſouer daunger or neceſſitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Apoynted places too praye in / maye not be neglectd.</head>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8582:44"/>BVt publike &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayers ſhuld be vſid in place apoynted / for aſſemblye of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregacion / from whence / whoſoeuer neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentlye extracte theym ſelfe is in nowyſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable / I meane not that to abſent frome that place is ſinne / becauſe it is more holy than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For the hole earthe created by God / is equal holy / but the promiſe made / that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer two or thre be gathered together in my name / there ſhall I be in the middes of them / condemneth all ſuche as contemneth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation / gathered in hys name / but marke wel gathered / I ſaye not to heare pyping / ſinging or playing / not to patter vpon beades or bokes / wherof they haue no vnderſtanding / not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Idolatrie / honoring that for God / which is no God indede / for with ſuch wil I neither ioyne my ſelfe in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer / nor receyuing of the externall ſacramentes / for in ſo doyng I ſhould affirme their ſuperſticion and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatrie / which I neuer wil do nor cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſail other to do to the ende.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶What is to be gathered in the name of Chriſt.</head>
                     <p>THis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion / which I meane / ſhould be gathered in the name of Ieſus Chriſt / that is to laude &amp; magnefye God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the infinite benefites they had receiued by his onely ſonne our Lord / in thys congrega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion ſhould be diſtributed the miſticall and laſt ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt / without ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or any more ceremonies then he hym ſelfe vſed / &amp; hys apoſtels after hym indiſtribution thereof / in thys congregacion ſhould inquiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:8582:44"/>
of the poore among them / &amp; ſufficient ſupport whyle the tyme of their next conuencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſhuld be prouided and diſtributed.</p>
                     <p>In this congregacion ſhoulde be made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayers / ſuche as all men hearing might vnderſtande that the hartes of all ſubſcribing to the voyce of one / mighte with vnfayned &amp; ferfent mynde ſay Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whoſoeuer do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe them ſelfe from ſuche a congregacion / but allace where ſhall it be founde / do declare them ſelfes too be no members of Chriſtes bodye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶For whome and at what tyme we ſhoulde praye.</head>
                     <p>FOr all men / <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. Vvhen and for vvhome vve ſhould praie.</note> &amp; at all times doth Paule commaund that we ſhall praye / &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally for ſuche of the houſholde of fayth / as ſuffer perſecucion / and when co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealths tyranniouſly we oppreſſed / then inceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſantly ſhoulde we call that God of hys infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy and power woll withſtande the violence of ſuche tyrauntes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶Gods ſentence maye be chaunged.</head>
                     <p>ANd when we ſe the plagues of God / hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger / peſtilence / or warre / commynge or apearing to raygne / then ſhould we with lamentable voyces &amp; repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting hartes call vnto God / that it wolde pleaſe hys mercy to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / for with ſuche as do aleage / that God may not chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hys ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; oure prayers / therefore to be in vayne / can I in no wyſe agree / beynge otherwyſe taughte in the ſcripture by hys infallable &amp; eternall veritie.
<pb facs="tcp:8582:45"/>
He ſayeth: I ſhall deſtroye this nacion frome the face of the earth / and when Moyſes adreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lorde procedeth ſaying: Suffer me that I may vtterly deſtroy them / and then Moyſes falleth on hys face flatling / and fourtye dayes contineweth in prayer / for the ſaluation of the people / to whome at the laſte obtayned forgeuenes. Dauid in the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment plague / lamentable calleth vnto God / &amp; the kynge of Niniue ſayeth:<note place="margin">2. King. laſt.</note> who knoweth / yf God ſhalbe conuerted and led backe by repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce.<note place="margin">Iona. 3.</note> And be tourned from the furor of hys wrath / that we periſh not / which examples &amp; ſcriptures are not written in vayne / but too certefye vs / that God of hys natiue goodnes will metigate by our prayers offered by Ieſus Chriſt / although he hath threatened to puniſh or preſently by puniſhing / which he doth teſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye by his owne wordes ſaying:<note place="margin">Ierem. 18</note> Yf I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheried againſt any nacion or people / that thei ſhalbe deſtroyed. And yf they repent of theyr iniquitie / it ſhall repent me of the euel / which I haue ſpoken agaynſt them.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>enes in praier.</note> This I write la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the great couldnes of men / which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo longe ſcorgis of God / is nothing kyndled to prayer by repentaunce / but carkeſe ſlepe in weked lyfe / euen as though their continuante warres / vrgent famyne / cotidian plagues off peſtilence / and other contagious inſolent and ſtraunge maladis / were not the preſent ſignes of Gods wrath prouoked by our iniquite.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>¶A plague threatned too Englande.</head>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="xvij" facs="tcp:8582:45"/>O Englande / <note place="margin">A plague threatened to Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</note> let thy inteſtiue batteries &amp; domeſticall murther / prouoke the to purety of lyfe / according to the worde / whiche openly hath bene proclaymed in the / other wiſe the cuppe of the Lordes wrathe / thou ſhalt ſhortly drinke of. The multitude ſhall not eſcape / but ſhall drynke the dregges / and haue the cuppe broken vpon their heades / <note place="margin">The godlye puniſſhed.</note> for iudgement beginninge in the houſe of the Lorde / commonly the leaſt offendor is fyrſt pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed / to prouoke the more weked too repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. But O Lorde / infinite mercye / yf thou ſhalt puniſhe / make not con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumacion / but cut awaye the proude &amp; luxuriant brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches / which beare no fruyte / and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon wealths / of ſuche as geue ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cour &amp; herber / to thy contempned meſſengers / which lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge haue ſuffred exile in deſerte / ſo be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="confession">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:46"/>
                  <head>¶Here after foloweth a Confeſſion</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Mnipotent and euerlaſting God father of our LORDE Ieſus Chryſte whoo be thy eternall prouidence / diſpoſes kyngdoms / as beſte ſeameth to thy wyſdom / we acknowledge and confeſſe thy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to be righteous in that thou haſt taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs / for our ingratitude and for a buſinge of thy moſt holy worde / our natiue Kyng &amp; earthlye comforter / iuſtly maye thou poure forth vpon vs the vttermoſte of thy plagues / for that we haue not knowen the dayes and tyme of oure mercifull viſitacion / we haue contempned thy worde / and diſpiſed thy mercies / we haue tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſed thy lawes / for deceytfully haue we wroughte euery man / with oure neyghbours oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we haue not abhorred / charitie / hath not apeared amonge vs as oure profeſſion requireth / we haue littel regarded the voyces of thy prophetes / thy threatninges we haue eſtemed vanytie and wynd / ſo that in vs / as of our ſelfs reſtes / nothinge worthy of thy mercies / for all are founde frutles / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the princes with the prophetes / as wythered trees apt and mete too be burnt in the fyre of thy eternall diſpleaſure. But o Lord / behold thy own mercy &amp; goodnes / that thou may purdge and remoue the moſte fylthye borden / of oure moſte horrible offences / let thy loue ouercome the ſeueritie of thy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / euen as it did in geuing to the world thy onely ſonne Ieſus / 
<pb n="xviij" facs="tcp:8582:46"/>
when all mankynde was loſt / and no obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was lefte in Adam nor in his ſede. Regenerate our hartes o Lorde by the ſtrength of the holy ghoſte / conuert thou vs / and we ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted / worke thou in vs vnfayned repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / and moue thou oure hartes too obey thy holy lawes. Beholde our trobles and apparant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction / and ſtaye the ſworde of thy venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce before it deuoure vs. Place aboue vs o Lorde for thy great mercies ſake / ſuch a head with ſuche rulers and maieſtrates as feareth thy name / and willeth the glory of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus to ſpred. Take not from vs the light of thy Euangely / and ſuffer thou no papiſtrie to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaile in this realme. Illuminate the harte off our ſoueraigne lady quene Marie / with prig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant giftes of thy holy ghoſte. And inflame the hartes of her cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl / with thy trew feare and loue / repreſſe thou the pryde of thoſe that wolde rebelle. And remoue frome all hartes the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte of the worde / let not our enemies reioyce at our deſtruction / but loke thou too the honor of thy owne name o Lorde / and let thy Goſpell be preached with boldines in this realme / if thy iuſtice muſt puniſh / then puniſh our bodies with the rodde of thy mercy. But o Lorde let vs neuer reuolte / nor turne backe to Idolatrie agayne. Mytigate the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of thoſe that perſecute vs / &amp; let vs not faynt vnder the croſſe of oure ſauiour / but aſſiſt vs with the holy ghoſte / euen to the ende.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="index">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:47"/>
                  <head>Here after fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the Table of this boke.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>A.</head>
                     <item>A confeſſion of Chriſtes moſte ſacred Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely / vpon the death of that moſte verteous &amp; moſte famous kyng Edward the .vi. fo. xvi.</item>
                     <item>A plague threatened to Englande. fo. xvi</item>
                     <item>A poynted places to praye in maye not be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. fo. xv.</item>
                     <item>Aungels maye not be mediators. fo. x.</item>
                     <item>Agaynſte ſuche as wolde haue mediators too Ieſus Chriſt. fo. xij.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>B.</head>
                     <item>Better it is to obey God then man. fo. xiij.</item>
                     <item>By whome we muſt praye. fo. ix.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>C.</head>
                     <item>Corporall thinges. fo. xij.</item>
                     <item>Comforte to the afflicted. fo. xiiij.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>D.</head>
                     <item>Dayly bread. fo. vi.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>F.</head>
                     <item>Fleſhe ſtriueth agaynſte the ſprete. fo. xiiij.</item>
                     <item>For who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; at what tyme we ſhould. fo. xvi.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>G.</head>
                     <item>Gods ſentence may be chaunged. fo. xvi.</item>
                     <item>God deliuereth hys choſen from. fo. vi.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>H.</head>
                     <item>How the ſprete maketh interceſſion. fo. iij.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <item>Ieſus Chriſt / God &amp; man is mediator. fo. x.</item>
                     <item>Impedimentes commeth of the weakenes off
<pb facs="tcp:8582:47"/>
the fleſhe. fo. xiiij.</item>
                     <item>Interceſſion to ſainctes. fo. x.</item>
                     <item>Ipocriſie is not alowed with God. fo. v</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>L.</head>
                     <item>Let euery man iudge hys owne hart. fo. iij.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>N.</head>
                     <item>Not to pray is ſynne moſt odious. fo. vij.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>O.</head>
                     <item>Obedience of Chriſt. fo. xi.</item>
                     <item>Obſeruacion in godly prayer. fo. ix</item>
                     <item>Of neceſſite we muſt haue a mediator. fo. ix.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>R.</head>
                     <item>Reddines of God to heare ſynners. fo. vij.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>S.</head>
                     <item>Sporris ſtire vs to prayer. fo. vi.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>T.</head>
                     <item>Turkes and Iewes / fo. ix.</item>
                     <item>The hope to obtayn our peticions / ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende vpon the promiſes of God. fo. vij.</item>
                     <item>The cauſe of theyr boldnes was Ieſus. fo. v.</item>
                     <item>The peticion of the ſprete. fo. xiiij.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>W.</head>
                     <item>What prayer is. fo. ij.</item>
                     <item>Who prayeth not in tribulation. fo. vi.</item>
                     <item>When ſynners are not harde of God. fo. iiij.</item>
                     <item>Why we ſhoulde praye / and alſo vnderſtande what we do praye. fo. iii.</item>
                     <item>What faſting / almoſe dedes are. fo. v.</item>
                     <item>When we be not herde. fo. x.</item>
                     <item>What is to be gathered in the name. fo. xv.</item>
                     <item>Who maketh other mediatours then Iheſus Chriſt taketh ouer from hym. fo. xi.</item>
                     <item>What ſhoulde be prayed for. fo. xiij.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8582:48"/>When and for whom we ſhould praye. fo. xv</item>
                     <item>Why God differreth or prolongeth to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs oure peticion. fo. xiij.</item>
                     <item>Where conſtaunte prayer is / there is graun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted peticion. fo. vij.</item>
                     <item>Who prayeth not. fo. iij.</item>
                     <item>What is to be obſerued in prayer. fo. ij.</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>¶Here endeth the Table.
<figure>
                        <head>GOD IS MY HELPER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8582:48"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
